<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Land and Language in Australian
Romanticism</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9261-8390</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Falk</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Michael Falk</string-name>

<email>michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Melbourne</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>


<abstract>
Eliza Hamilton Dunlop (1796-1880) and Charles Harpur (1813-1867) were
two of the most important Romantic poets of colonial New South Wales. In
this article, I consider their engagement with Indigenous Australian
languages. In ‘Native Song’ (1848), Dunlop provides a transcription and
translation of verse composed by her informant Wulatji (fl. 1840s), a
famous Awabakal poet. In <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> (c. 1844),
Harpur enriches his description of Australian landscapes with a dozen
words learned from Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and Wonnarua informants. I
contrast Dunlop’s universalist approach to Indigenous langauge with
Harpur’s particularist approach, and contextualise their poetry in
British philosophy of language. Dunlop and Harpur use Indigenous
language to present Australia as a land steeped in poetry, but their
recognition of Indigenous poetry undermines their own attempts to make
themselves at home in the colony.
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Harpur, Charles; Dunlop, Eliza Hamilton; Wulatji; Romanticism;
philosophy of language; terra nullius</kwd>
</kwd-group>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>1 Introduction</title>
  <p>To occupy Australia, its European invaders had to name it. This was
  not merely a matter of naming places, though that of course was
  crucial. They also needed to name the things that made the places.
  They needed to name the trees that dropped their autumn bark, the
  deer-like creatures that hopped on two legs, the fires that ripped
  through crackling scrubland. They needed to name the fickle weather,
  the whirling dust, the intermittent streams. They needed to name
  hundreds of parrots and pigeons and snakes and dragons. They needed to
  name the people from whom they took the land. To conquer Australia,
  they “conquered space.” With a touch of the namer’s wand, they changed
  a strange land “into a familiar world of routes and places”
  (<xref alt="Tuan 1977, 83" rid="ref-tuan_space_1977" ref-type="bibr">Tuan
  1977, 83</xref>).</p>
  <p>The invaders mined Indigenous languages for names. Indigenous names
  had the advantage of establishment. The Indigenous name is the “real
  and proper” name, thought Lachlan Macquarie (quoted in
  <xref alt="Carter 2010, 328" rid="ref-carter_road_2010" ref-type="bibr">Carter
  2010, 328</xref>). But what the invaders found “real and proper” was
  not always what the conquered found “real and proper.” In Australia,
  the Europeans debased words such as <italic>gin</italic> and
  <italic>lubra</italic>, while mixing myriad other words from myriad
  tongues into the new Australian English.</p>
  <p>In the 1840s, two invader-poets observed this situation and
  attempted to rectify it. Eliza Hamilton Dunlop and Charles Harpur were
  humanitarians who recognised the value of Indigenous poetry. They
  praised Indigenous Australian languages, and borrowed Indigenous words
  to enrich their poetic diction. Thus they attempted to conquer space
  and make themselves at home, while also recognising the prior claims
  of Indigenous Australians to the land.</p>
  <p>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop (1796-1880) was the Irish wife of the
  Protector of Aborigines in Wollombi (see
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-map">Figure 1</xref>). She befriended a
  local poet, Wulatji (fl. 1840s), learned his tongue, and published a
  transcription and translation of his poetry in the <italic>Sydney
  Morning Herald</italic>
  (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
  1848</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref> Twenty-first
  century critics have praised Dunlop’s appreciation for Indigenous
  cultures, while noting her “colonialism” and “cultural appropriation”
  by more recent standards
  (<xref alt="O’Leary 2004" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004" ref-type="bibr">O’Leary
  2004</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston 2021, 47" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 47</xref>). Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  has verified the accuracy of her translation, and used it to
  reconstruct Wulatji’s song-writing practices. He also highlights a
  remarkable fact about Dunlop’s translation, which has hitherto escaped
  literary analysis: she translates many of Wulatji’s words by
  <italic>other</italic> Indigenous words, often from far-flung
  languages.</p>
  <p>Charles Harpur (1813-1867) was a currency lad, born to convict
  parents on the banks of Deerubbin (the Hawkesbury-Nepean; see
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-map">Figure 1</xref>). His poetry is
  voluminous and varied, but the violence of the frontier, the ignorance
  of the settler, and the brutality of empire are key themes in many of
  his poems. He has been judged complicit in the imaginative
  expropriation of Aboriginal lands
  (<xref alt="Van Toorn 1992" rid="ref-van_toorn_terrors_1992" ref-type="bibr">Van
  Toorn 1992</xref>), and some of his poems do imagine Australia as a
  place of “solitude profound” before European settlement
  (<xref alt="Harpur 2019, h665a" rid="ref-harpur_charles_2019" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  2019, h665a</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref> In
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> (1843-1867), Harpur reckons with
  his own contradictory impulses. He acknowledges Indigenous Australians
  as the “former lords of the soil,” and includes 12 Indigenous words in
  the text of the poem. In a series of footnotes, he localises the words
  to particular Indigenous groups, and argues for the appropriateness of
  Indigenous words to poetry. The poem has a complex textual history—as
  do nearly all Harpur’s poems
  (<xref alt="Eggert 2016" rid="ref-eggert_charles_2016" ref-type="bibr">Eggert
  2016</xref>). The earliest evidence for the poem is an excerpt
  published in the <italic>Weekly Register</italic> in 1843
  (<xref alt="Harpur 1843" rid="ref-harpur_australian_1843" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  1843</xref>). At that time, Harpur was living at Jerrys Plains, in the
  upper Hunter Valley. All the surviving complete versions of the poem,
  however, date to the 1860s, when Harpur was living far to the south in
  Eurobodalla. Although Harpur revised the poem considerably,
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> retains is character as poem of the
  1840s, extolling the beauties of the “loud Nepean,” “old Hawkesbury”
  and “rapid Hunter” rivers where Harpur spent his youth and early
  adulthood (h209-bf). It is nonetheless tricky to precisely localise
  the poem’s Indigenous vocabulary.</p>
  <fig id="fig-map">
    <caption><p>Figure 1: Deerubbin and the Hunter in the 1840s,
    indicating languages, settlements and rivers mentioned in the text.
    Sources: Geoscience Australia
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-geoscience_australia_geodata_2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>);
    Nominatim; Lissarrague
    (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>);
    Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>);
    Jones
    (<xref alt="2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>);
    Austlang.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="harpur-dunlop-wulatji_files/figure-jats/fig-map-1.png" />
  </fig>
  <p>My comparison of Harpur and Dunlop has two aims. The first aim is
  to contrast Dunlop’s and Harpur’s poetics: I argue that Dunlop is a
  <italic>universalist</italic>, while Harpur is a
  <italic>particularist</italic>. The second aim is to clarify the
  problem of <italic>linguistic representation</italic>—or more
  verbosely, the <italic>literary representation of Indigenous
  languages</italic>.</p>
  <p>Both Dunlop and Harpur represent Indigenous language for
  humanitarian ends. Although Dunlop was highly sensitive to the
  differences between people, her “sentimental” poetics relies on the
  universality of human feelings to justify the universality of human
  rights
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021</xref>). Thus she attempts to demonstrate the universality of the
  poetic impulse by transcribing and translating a sample of Awabakal
  poetry. By contrast, Harpur attempts to do justice to Indigenous
  ecopoetics by drawing a link between the euphony of particular
  Indigenous words and the ecological knowledge of particular Indigenous
  people. Dunlop’s universalism and Harpur’s particularism have both
  been subject to scholarly critique, but have never been compared. I
  perform the comparison in sections
  <xref alt="2" rid="eliza-hamilton-dunlop-universalism">2</xref> and
  <xref alt="3" rid="charles-harpur-particularism">3</xref>.</p>
  <p>Dunlop and Harpur also raise the broader question of how to
  represent a language. Both Harpur and Dunlop wish to represent
  Indigenous languages as <italic>poetic</italic>, but they do so in
  different ways. Dunlop produces a <italic>transcription</italic>,
  <italic>translation</italic> and <italic>glossary</italic>; Harpur
  produces <italic>words</italic> and <italic>philological
  footnotes</italic> embedded in an original poem. These different forms
  of representation convey different ideas about the nature of
  Indigenous language. Dunlop presents Wulatji’s language (the Hunter
  River Lake Macquarie language, or HRLM), as <italic>syntactic</italic>
  and <italic>literary.</italic> Harpur presents the various languages
  of his poem, namely Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and HRLM, as
  <italic>verbal</italic> and <italic>oral</italic>. Despite these
  differences, Dunlop and Harpur draw on a similar stock of ideas about
  human language, rooted in the empiricist linguistics that then reigned
  in the English-speaking world. I demonstrate this shared background in
  <xref alt="section 4" rid="linguistic-representation-and-the-conquest-of-space">section
  4</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="eliza-hamilton-dunlop-universalism">
  <title>2 Eliza Hamilton Dunlop: Universalism</title>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Since morning stars first sang in prayerful praise,
    Since Adam’s hymns resounded over space,
    Or Sinai’s hill trembled in glory’s blaze;
    Immortal song hath had acknowledged place.
    (<xref alt="Dunlop 1872b, ll. 1–4" rid="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    1872b, ll. 1–4</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>For Dunlop, “song” is a universal feature of human nature. In the
  opening lines of “Poesy,” she hears song in three places: in nature
  (the “morning stars”), in oral tradition (“Adam’s hymns”), and in
  written literature (“On Sinai’s hill,” where Moses receives the tables
  of the law). In all these places, the same force of “song” is heard.
  At all <italic>times</italic>, too, this “song” is heard, for it is
  “Immortal.” Song is immortal and ubiquitous, Dunlop continues, because
  it is an “Essence inherent of the sentient mind”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop 1872b, l. 5" rid="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  1872b, l. 5</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref> Always and
  everywhere, humans are poets.</p>
  <p>Dunlop’s belief in the universality of song had deep ethical and
  intellectual roots. She was a “sentimentalist,” whose poetry teaches
  that “the emotional experiences of others are similar to our own”
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021, 91" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021, 91</xref>). She was an “internationalist,” whose poetry
  describes the struggle for freedom among all the oppressed peoples of
  the British Empire
  (<xref alt="Wu 2021, 60" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021" ref-type="bibr">Wu
  2021, 60</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston and Webby 2021, 9" rid="ref-johnston_proud_2021" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  and Webby 2021, 9</xref>). She was a polyglot, whose poems speak in
  many tongues
  (<xref alt="Wafer 2021, 158–59" rid="ref-wafer_unmapping_2021" ref-type="bibr">Wafer
  2021, 158–59</xref>). Thus she expressed her humanitarian ideals in
  the rhetoric, content and vocabulary of her poetry.</p>
  <p>As Rudy
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)
  insists, Dunlop’s universalism was not naive. She grew up in Ireland
  in the wake of the United Irish uprising and the abolition of the
  Irish parliament. She visited India, where she befriended her
  “half-caste” sisters.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref> She
  settled in Australia, where she displayed an exceptional facility for
  Indigenous languages, particularly their phonetics
  (<xref alt="Johnston 2021, 46" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 46</xref>), and where she campaigned publicly for the rights of
  Indigenous Australians. In all these places, she was sensitive to
  local conditions. She published some 100 poems in Irish and Australian
  newspapers; when she did so, she chose her words carefully for local
  readers, especially when republishing Irish works in Australia
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021, 94" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021, 94</xref>). Her universalism was modulated by her pragmatic
  sense of audience.</p>
  <p>It is in this context that we should understand her transcription
  and translation of Wulatji’s poetry. The transcription is short enough
  to quote in full. Its language is Awabakal, recognised today as a
  variety of the Hunter River Lake Macquarie language (HRLM):</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba wonung bulkirra umbilinto bulwarra;
    Pital burra kultan wirripang bunto
    Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba turrama berrambo, burra kilkoa:
    Kurri wi, raratoa yella walliko,
    Yulo Moane, woinya, birung poro bulliko[.]
    Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba kan wullung, Makora, kokein,
    Mip-pa-rai, kekul, wimbi murr ring kirrika:
    Nge a runba mura ke-en kulbun kulbun murrung.
    (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
    1848</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>It is difficult to say what precisely this is a transcription
  <italic>of</italic>. O’Leary
  (<xref alt="2004, 92" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004" ref-type="bibr">2004,
  92</xref>) argues from manuscript evidence that Dunlop fashioned a
  single poem from “three short songs” by Wulatji. In a manuscript she
  prepared in the 1870s, she does indeed label the three sections “Song
  1,” “Song 2” and “Song 3”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop, n.d." rid="ref-dunlop_vase_nodate" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop,
  n.d.</xref>, image 60; printed in
  <xref alt="Dunlop 2021, 194" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  2021, 194</xref>). In both the published version and the manuscript,
  she gives each section the heading “Nung-Ngung”
  (<italic>nannguyn</italic>, “song”). Despite this evidence, Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  argues that Wulatji’s poetry should actually be seen as four “verses”
  of two lines each. He gives two arguments: the four-verse
  interpretation makes the poetry more metrically consistent
  (<xref alt="2017, 204" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  204</xref>); and the textual evidence cannot be trusted, because there
  is no record of Dunlop and Wulatji’s conversations
  (<xref alt="2017, 202" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  202</xref>). Did Wulatji produce one or more discrete texts at
  Dunlop’s request, knowing they might be published? Did he perform at a
  ceremony or gathering that Dunlop observed? Did he produce a series of
  verse-examples to try and teach her about Awabakal versification? Did
  he improvise a performance to impress
  her?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref> Dunlop herself provides
  evidence that it may be foolish to precisely number the poems in
  Wulatji’s text. In the manuscript version of the poem, she notes that
  Indigenous songs are short and “often repeated in a variety of
  cadence”
  (<xref alt="2021, 194" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021" ref-type="bibr">2021,
  194</xref>). How many different verses would a poet like Wulatji
  “repeat” in a single performance? It is not necessarily the case that
  his poetry could be neatly divided into discrete “poems” independent
  of one another.</p>
  <p>Dunlop preserves this ambiguity in her transcription and
  translation. Her title, “Native Poetry,” does not specify the number
  of poems. When she adapted her translation into an original song for
  Isaac Nathan, she used a similarly indeterminate title, “Pialla
  Wollombi,” which she glosses as “the poetry or language of Wollombi”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop and Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  and Wulatji 1848</xref>). All this is to suggest that Dunlop does not
  transcribe a <italic>text</italic>, but rather a
  <italic>corpus</italic> of Awabakal verse. She provides the reader a
  sample of Wulatji’s poetry, and shapes it into a single translation
  for readerly consumption—for the <italic>translation</italic>, unlike
  the transcription, certainly comprises a single text:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Our home is the gibber-gunyah,
    Where hill joins hill on high;
    Where the turruma and berrambo,
    Like sleeping serpents lie;
    And the rushing of wings, as the wangas pass,
    Sweeps the wallaby’s print from the glistening grass.
    Ours are the makoro gliding,
    Deep in the shady pool;
    For our spear is sure, and the prey secure…
    Kanin, or the bright gherool.
    Our lubras sleep by the bato clear,
    That the Amygest’s track hath never been near.
    Ours is the koolema flowing
    With precious kirrika stored;
    For fleet the foot, and keen the eye,
    That seeks the nukkung’s hoard;
    And the glances are bright, and the footsteps are free,
    When we dance in the shade of the karakon tree.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>There are many remarkable features of this translation, but for our
  purposes, the most important aspect is its vocabulary
  (<xref alt="Table 1" rid="tbl-dunlop-lang">Table 1</xref>). Dunlop
  includes 15 Indigenous words in her translation. Five of these had
  already been incorporated into Australian English by 1848:
  “gibber-gunyah,” “wallaby,” “wanga,” “lubra”, and probably “koolema”
  (<xref alt="Dixon et al. 2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006" ref-type="bibr">Dixon
  et al. 2006</xref>). She nonetheless includes two of
  them—“gibber-gunyah” and “wanga”—in the poem’s Glossary. The other 10
  words probably appear here in English verse for the first time, and
  probably all originate in Wulatji’s speech (“gherool” and “Amygest”
  being the difficult cases).</p>
  <fig id="tbl-dunlop-lang">
    <caption><p>Table 1: Indigenous vocabulary in Dunlop’s translation
    of Wulatji. Sources: Wafer
    (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>);
    HRLM
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague 2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague
    2006</xref>); Darkinyung
    (<xref alt="Jones 2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008" ref-type="bibr">Jones
    2008</xref>); Gamilaraay
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
    Ash, and Giacon 2003</xref>); Sydney
    (<xref alt="Troy 1993" rid="ref-troy_sydney_1993" ref-type="bibr">Troy
    1993</xref>); Dixon et al.
    (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</p></caption>
    <table-wrap>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="10%" />
          <col width="7%" />
          <col width="9%" />
          <col width="33%" />
          <col width="41%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Dunlop’s translation</th>
            <th align="left">Wulatji’s text</th>
            <th align="left">Dunlop’s definition</th>
            <th align="left">HRLM equivalents</th>
            <th align="left">Other equivalents</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gibber-gunyah</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Cave in the rock</td>
            <td align="left">kuyung ~ kuyang <italic>camp, camp fire;
            also town</italic></td>
            <td align="left">giba <italic>stone or rock</italic>, gunya
            <italic>hut</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">turruma</td>
            <td align="left">turrama</td>
            <td align="left">War arms</td>
            <td align="left">TaRama <italic>war boomerang</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">berrambo</td>
            <td align="left">berrambo</td>
            <td align="left">War arms</td>
            <td align="left">pirampu <italic>waddy; club
            (Wafer)</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wanga</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">A species of pigeon</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wungawunga <italic>Wonga pigeon</italic>
            (Sydney); wangawanga <italic>Wonga pigeon</italic>
            (Darkinyung)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wallaby</td>
            <td align="left">buntoa</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">walapi ~ walapay <italic>wallaby</italic>;
            paNTarr <italic>kangaroo</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wulaba <italic>rock wallaby</italic>
            (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">makoro</td>
            <td align="left">Makoro</td>
            <td align="left">Fish</td>
            <td align="left">makurr <italic>fish</italic></td>
            <td align="left">magura <italic>fish</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kanim</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Eel</td>
            <td align="left">kaNiyn ~ KaNang <italic>freshwater
            eel</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gherool</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Mullet</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">djirul <italic>mullet</italic>
            (Darkinyung)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">lubra</td>
            <td align="left">mura ke-en</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">marr[a]kiyn <italic>young maiden, woman,
            girl</italic></td>
            <td align="left">[The etymology of <italic>lubra</italic> is
            unknown; possibly from a Tasmanian language] (Dixon et
            al)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">bato</td>
            <td align="left">kokein</td>
            <td align="left">Water</td>
            <td align="left">paTu, kukuyn <italic>fresh
            water</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Amygest</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">White fellow</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">koolema</td>
            <td align="left">wimbi</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wimpi <italic>vessel made from the knots of
            trees and used as baskets or bowls</italic></td>
            <td align="left">guliman <italic>coolamon</italic>
            (Gamilaraay)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kirrika</td>
            <td align="left">kirrika</td>
            <td align="left">Honey</td>
            <td align="left">kiR[i]ka <italic>white honey</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">nukkung</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Wild bee</td>
            <td align="left">Nakang <italic>native bee</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">karakun</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Oak Tree</td>
            <td align="left">karakaNpa <italic>place of
            swamp-oaks</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </fig>
  <p>What is remarkable is the relationship between Dunlop’s words and
  Wulatji’s. We might expect Dunlop only to introduce Indigenous words
  in her poem if they are present in Wulatji’s text, or common in
  Australian English. But this is not her practice. In just four cases,
  Dunlop incorporates a word from Wulatji’s text into her translation:
  “turruma”, “berrambo”, “makoro” and “kirrika.” In the other cases, she
  either inserts a new word into the poem (e.g. “wanga,” “nukkung”) or
  translates one of Wulatji’s words by a <italic>different</italic>
  Indigenous word (e.g. “kokein” → “bato”, “wimbi” → “koolema”). Her
  translation ultimately incorporates vocabulary from at least three or
  four Australian languages, but in neither the text nor the Glossary
  does she indicate which languages they are. Dunlop effectively
  develops her own poetic language, combining English, Wulatji’s own
  speech, and the speech of other Indigenous peoples across Eastern NSW.
  She confers unity on Wulatji’s verses, combining them into a single
  poem, and she confers unity on the languages of the colony, combining
  them into a single tongue. How should we interpret this unity?</p>
  <p>Dunlop’s translation is a representation of Indigenous speech. Thus
  it has two interlinked aims: it must capture the lyrical qualities of
  Wulatji’s verse; and it must signal its Indigenous Australian origin
  to the reader. In this light, the inclusion of familiar words such as
  “gibber-gunyah” and “wallaby” makes sense. These words signal to the
  reader that this is an “Australian” poem. The choice to translate
  Wulatji’s words by other words sometimes serves this purpose of
  familiarisation (e.g. “mura ke-en” → “lubra”), and sometimes seems to
  be an aesthetic decision: e.g. Dunlop presumably found “bato clear”
  more euphonious than “kokein clear” or alternative phrasings. The
  poem’s rhyme and metre also serve these dual purposes of
  familiarisation and exoticism. The rhymes follow the familiar
  <italic>ababcc</italic> scheme of Shakespeare’s <italic>Venus and
  Adonis</italic> (1593). Meanwhile the accentual metre emulates the old
  ballads that represented “tradition” for Romantic readers. The number
  of beats follows a fixed pattern in each stanza (3-3-4-3-4-4), while
  the rhythm shifts freely between binary and ternary. In sum, Dunlop
  presents Wulatji’s poetry as though it is an ancient ballad in an
  “invented tradition” of Australian verse, the kind of poem you might
  encounter in Thomas Percy’s <italic>Reliques of Ancient English
  Poetry</italic> (1765) or Walter Scott’s <italic>Minstrelsy of the
  Scottish Border</italic> (1802).</p>
  <p>To turn Wulatji’s poem into a “Relique” of Australian verse, Dunlop
  amplifies the text. Wulatji’s original text is not remotely
  ballad-like. It has a terseness that bespeaks its rich metaphysical
  background. Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017, 206" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  206</xref>) translates the first verse thus:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Ours is the place where the mountains cohabit with the heights
    The eaglehawks and wallabies are happy</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>When she chooses, Dunlop captures the literal sense of Wulatji’s
  verse well, e.g. “wonung bulkirra umbilinto bulwarra” → “where hill
  joins hill on high.” But she generally amplifies the verse to conform
  with European expectations of the lyric. Human embodiment is implicit
  in Wulatji’s poem. Dunlop makes it explicit, indicating that the
  mountains are Wulatji’s “home.” The senses are muted in Wulatji’s
  poem. Dunlop invokes the senses, so that the birds have “rushing
  wings,” and the wallabies play on the “glistening grass.” She also,
  inexplicably, turns Wulatji’s “wirripang” (“eaglehawk”) into a Wonga
  pigeon. These amplifications are typical of Dunlop’s translation. She
  inserts individual persons into the poem, placing their bodies in the
  landscape and invoking their sensory experiences of nature.</p>
  <p>Dunlop thus presents Wulatji’s verse as <italic>syntactic</italic>
  and <italic>literary</italic>. It is not the individual words of his
  poetry that matter, but their connection into smoothly-flowing verse.
  And though Wulatji’s verse is oral rather than written, Dunlop
  presents it as implictly literary, like the ancient “Reliques” of
  English verse preserved in book and manuscript. Dunlop emphasises the
  syntax and literacy of Wulatji’s verse in her introduction to the
  poem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>There is a god of Poesy, Wallatu, who composes music, and who,
    without temple, shrine, or statue, is as universally acknowledged as
    if his oracles were breathed by Belus or Osiris: he comes in dreams,
    and transports the individual to some sunny hill, where he is
    inspired with the supernatural gift.
    (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
    1848</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Wulatji’s poetry is syntactic because it does not comprise
  individual words. Instead it comes complete, in the form of “oracles”
  delivered by divine inspiration. Wulatji’s poetry is literary because
  the god of his inspiration, Wallatu, is the same in kind as the gods
  of the Celts (Belus) and Egyptians (Osiris), whose writings lie at the
  origins of Western civilisation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>
  Dunlop the Irish writer recognises in Wulatji a fellow Celt. And this
  is unsurprising, because “Poesy” is universal, and can be recognised
  as easily in Australia as anywhere else. Thus the freedom of Dunlop’s
  translation. She does not translate the literal sense of the words,
  but communicates the “Poesy” that inspires them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="charles-harpur-particularism">
  <title>3 Charles Harpur: Particularism</title>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>A thousand bright particulars are given,
    And they outshine the very stars of heaven! (“Ideality”, h185b)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Harpur’s poem is on a grander scale than Dunlop’s. <italic>The
  Kangaroo Hunt, or A Morning in the Mountains: A Descriptive Poem in
  Six Parts: By Charles Harpur. An Australian</italic> is a long and
  ambitious work that has been described as “Australia’s first epic
  poem”
  (<xref alt="Gelder and Weaver 2020, 81" rid="ref-gelder_colonial_2020" ref-type="bibr">Gelder
  and Weaver 2020, 81</xref>). It describes an “idealised” kangaroo hunt
  that lasts from sunrise to sunset. As the youthful party of white
  hunters harry the kangaroo, Harpur describes the sights and sounds of
  the Australian bush, expanding on the verse in detailed footnotes. The
  poem pulls in two directions. In one direction, Harpur seeks to
  “idealise” the hunt, blending the details of many possible hunts into
  “one Eden-piece embathed with a luminous atmosphere of sentiment”
  (h209-af). In another direction, Harpur seeks to capture specific
  details of land and language, to capture the particular qualities of
  each bird, tree, geological feature—or Indigenous word. We will see
  that in his hunt for particularity, Harpur presents Indigenous
  languages as primarily <italic>oral</italic> and
  <italic>verbal</italic>. A language comprises words that are spoken by
  particular people in particular places.</p>
  <p>Harpur uses 12 Indigenous words in either the body of the poem or
  its footnotes
  (<xref alt="Table 2" rid="tbl-harpur-lang">Table 2</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>
  Generally speaking, Harpur’s transcriptions are sound, and it is not
  difficult to look up the words in a modern dictionary. It is
  nonetheless difficult to identify the languages of Harpur’s poem, for
  two main reasons. The first reason is lack of biographical evidence.
  Harpur does not name his informants, nor does he describe precisely
  where he encountered them. The only geographic detail he provides is
  in his footnote on the words “jimbuc” and “whirring”, which I discuss
  below. The second reason lies in the textual record. Harpur began the
  poem in the 1840s, while living on the Hunter, and completed it in the
  1860s, while living in Eurobodalla. With the exception of a single
  extract published in the <italic>Weekly Register</italic> in 1843, all
  the surviving versions of the poem date to the 1860s
  (<xref alt="Harpur 1843" rid="ref-harpur_australian_1843" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  1843</xref>). Only <italic>one</italic> Indigenous word, “duaralli,”
  appears in the 1843 newspaper extract. When did Harpur learn and
  insert the other words? Despite these problems, it is possible to find
  all but one of Harpur’s words in modern dictionaries.</p>
  <fig id="tbl-harpur-lang">
    <caption><p>Table 2: Indigenous Vocabulary in <italic>The Kangaroo
    Hunt</italic>. Sources: Darkinyung
    (<xref alt="Jones 2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008" ref-type="bibr">Jones
    2008</xref>); HRLM
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague 2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague
    2006</xref>); Gamilaraay
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
    Ash, and Giacon 2003</xref>); Wiradjuri
    (<xref alt="Grant, Grant, and Rudder 2010" rid="ref-grant_new_2010" ref-type="bibr">Grant,
    Grant, and Rudder 2010</xref>); Dhurga
    (<xref alt="Ellis et al. 2020" rid="ref-ellis_dhurga_2020" ref-type="bibr">Ellis
    et al. 2020</xref>); Sydney
    (<xref alt="Troy 1993" rid="ref-troy_sydney_1993" ref-type="bibr">Troy
    1993</xref>); also Jim Wafer, personal communication.</p></caption>
    <table-wrap>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="5%" />
          <col width="41%" />
          <col width="9%" />
          <col width="10%" />
          <col width="14%" />
          <col width="7%" />
          <col width="15%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Harpur’s word</th>
            <th align="left">Harpur’s definition</th>
            <th align="left">Referent</th>
            <th align="left">Darkinyung</th>
            <th align="left">HRLM</th>
            <th align="left">Gamilaraay</th>
            <th align="left">Other</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Euroka</td>
            <td align="left">“an aboriginal name of the sun”</td>
            <td align="left">the sun</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">panyal</td>
            <td align="left">yaraay</td>
            <td align="left">yurraga (Wiradjuri); yuraga (Dhurga)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">bidawong</td>
            <td align="left">“flying squirrel”</td>
            <td align="left">glider</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">pitjang</td>
            <td align="left">bagu</td>
            <td align="left">budha-rang (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kindyne</td>
            <td align="left">“ring-tailed possum”</td>
            <td align="left">ring-tailed possum</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>gindang</bold></td>
            <td align="left">wilay <italic>possum</italic></td>
            <td align="left">garrawir</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gooburra</td>
            <td align="left">“the large kind of king-fisher which is
            commonly known by the tasteful and poetic sobriquet of the
            Laughing Jackass”</td>
            <td align="left">kookaburra</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>kukaparr</bold></td>
            <td align="left">gugurrgaagaa</td>
            <td align="left">gugubarra (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">teleltella</td>
            <td align="left">“a large and solitary kind of
            bell-bird”</td>
            <td align="left">crested bellbird</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">banbandhuluwi</td>
            <td align="left">dilbanyi <italic>ring–to ring as a
            bell</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">warragl</td>
            <td align="left">“an aboriginal name of the native dog”</td>
            <td align="left">wild dog</td>
            <td align="left">miri <italic>dog, wild dog</italic></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>waRikal</bold></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wuragal (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">yerowala</td>
            <td align="left">“blue-mountain parrot”</td>
            <td align="left">rainbow lorikeet</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>wagarala</bold>
            <italic>parrot</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wakalarr ~ wakilarr <italic>red parrot;
            rosella</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wiragala <italic>australian
            ringneck</italic> (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">duaralli</td>
            <td align="left">“the kangaroo-rat;” attributed to “the
            blacks of the Hunter” in 1843, but to “blacks of the
            interior” in 1867 (h209-df)</td>
            <td align="left">eastern bettong</td>
            <td align="left">dhurawayi</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>dhurrawaay</bold></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">maroo</td>
            <td align="left">“a sort of brush iron-wood”</td>
            <td align="left">?grey box</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>maru</bold> <italic>thorny
            bush</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wallaroo</td>
            <td align="left">“wallaroo”; “the male … [is] almost black,
            and the female … [is] a sort of cream color”</td>
            <td align="left">eastern wallaroo</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>walaru</bold> <italic>black
            kangaroo</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">yulama</td>
            <td align="left">wularu (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">jimbuc</td>
            <td align="left">“a little shag-haired species of kangaroo;”
            metaphorically, “sheep”</td>
            <td align="left">brush-tailed rock wallaby</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>dhimba</bold>
            <italic>sheep</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">whirring</td>
            <td align="left">name for “jimbuck” among the people of “the
            Hawksbury mountains”</td>
            <td align="left">brush-tailed rock wallaby</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>wirayn</bold></td>
            <td align="left">wayiring <italic>wallaby</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wan.guy</td>
            <td align="left">wirrang (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </fig>
  <p>The linguistic evidence suggests that the language of the poem is
  primarily Darkinyung, HRLM and Gamilaraay. This finding is consistent
  with the one biographical clue that Harpur provides in the poem. The
  clue lies in the word “jimbuc,” which Harpur attributes to the “Blacks
  of the Hunter,” as opposed to the “blacks of the Hawksbury
  mountains:”</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Jimbuc is an aboriginal name of little shag-haired species of
    kangaroo which is peculiar to mountain copses. It may be called the
    mountain wallaby, being in relation to the wallaroo what the common
    wallaby is to the kangaroo proper. The jimbuc is the least elegant
    in its form, and the dullest in its nature, of all the kangaroo
    kinds—of all such at least as I happen to be acquainted with. The
    Blacks of the Hunter call the sheep jimbuc, no doubt from a
    resemblance, however remote, arising out of the hairy shagginess of
    the one and the woolliness of the other. But this, like most other
    of our indigenous animals, is named variously by the aboriginal
    tribes of different localities: and is (or was) known amongst the
    Hawksbury mountains by the native name of <italic>whirring</italic>.
    (h209-gf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>By the “Hawksbury mountains,” Harpur presumably refers to the rocky
  highlands that lie between Deebrubbin and the Hunter Valley. If this
  is so, then the language he would most likely encounter in that region
  is Darkinyung. The first road between Sydney and the Hunter Valley ran
  through this region Harpur calls the “Hawksbury mountains,” so Harpur
  is likely to have traversed the region numerous times when moving
  between the Hunter, Deerubbin and Sydney.</p>
  <p>The case for “the Blacks of the Hunter” is more difficult. In the
  1840s and 50s, Harpur spent most of his time moving around Singleton
  and Jerrys Plains. According to Lissarrague
  (<xref alt="2006, 13" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006" ref-type="bibr">2006,
  13</xref>), this was a bilingual zone. Towards the east, the Wonnarua
  and Geawagal spoke varieties of HRLM, Wulatji’s tongue. Towards the
  west, the people spoke another language, and the available sources are
  unclear what it was. Lissarrague suspects it was either Gamilaraay or
  Darkinyung. Since Darkinyung is the most likely candidate for Harpur’s
  language of the “Hawksbury mountains,” his language of the “Hunter” is
  more likely to be Gamilaraay. This is broadly consistent with
  <xref alt="Table 2" rid="tbl-harpur-lang">Table 2</xref>, which shows
  that there is a compelling Darkinyung, HRLM, or Gamilaraay equivalent
  for nine of Harpur’s 12 Indigenous words (marked in bold).</p>
  <p>The example of “jimbuc” supports this general picture. Today,
  <italic>jumbuck</italic> is cherished by settler Australians as a
  slang word for sheep, immortalised in the popular song
  <italic>Waltzing Matilda</italic>. Dixon et al.
  (<xref alt="2006, 56" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006" ref-type="bibr">2006,
  56</xref>) suggest that the word may derive from English
  <italic>jump</italic>, or perhaps from the Gamilaraay word
  <italic>dhimba</italic>, but admit that neither hypothesis can be
  “confirmed.” Harpur’s footnote provides concerete support for the
  hypothesis that <italic>jumbuck</italic> derives from Gamilaraay
  <italic>dhimba</italic>. The hypothesis gains strength given the
  specificity of Harpur’s description: Harpur insists that the word
  referred specifically to the “mountain wallaby,” which from his
  description is clearly the brush-tailed rock wallaby
  (<italic>Petrogale penicillata</italic>). The compilers of the modern
  <italic>Gamilaraay-Yuwalaraay-Yuwaalayaay</italic> dictionary were
  unable to find a word specifically for the brush-tailed-rock wallaby,
  and record the word <italic>dhimba</italic> solely in its meaning of
  <italic>sheep</italic>
  (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003, 62" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
  Ash, and Giacon 2003, 62</xref>). If we can trust Harpur’s testimony
  on this point, then the old riddle of <italic>jumbuck</italic> is
  solved, and we can be surer that some of Harpur’s informants in the
  Hunter spoke Gamilaraay.</p>
  <p>Although it seems certain that Harpur learned most of the words
  directly from Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and HRLM speakers, some of the
  words present problems. It is of course quite probable that Harpur
  learned the words “wallaroo,” “gooburra” and “warragl” simply by
  learning English: these words had passed into Australian English from
  Wiradjuri and the Sydney language by the 1830s
  (<xref alt="Dixon et al. 2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006" ref-type="bibr">Dixon
  et al. 2006</xref>). The real problem words are “Euroka,” “bidawong”
  and “teleltella.”</p>
  <p>The origin of “teleltella” is most obscure. Wafer (personal
  communication) suggests that <italic>dilbanyi</italic>, a word in the
  Sydney Language, could be a possible source. Gamilaraay
  <italic>banbandhuluwi</italic> has a promising number of syllables and
  the correct meaning, but the vowels and consonants differ considerably
  from Harpur’s transcription. It is possible that “teleltella”
  represents a hitherto unattested Darkinyung or HRLM word: no word for
  “crested bellbird” appears in either dictionary.</p>
  <p>The other problem words, “bidawong” and “Euroka,” are attested in
  Wiradjuri, a language spoken in regions bordering Darkinyung, HRLM and
  Gamilaraay. “Euroka” is also attested in Dhurga, the local language of
  the south coast where Harpur was living in the 1860s. The data suggest
  three hypotheses: (1) Harpur had Wiradjuri informants; (2) “bidawong”
  and/or “Euroka” were present in Darkinyung but are hitherto
  unattested; (3) Harpur inserted the word “Euroka” into the poem after
  he learned it from Dhurga speakers in the 1860s. If hypothesis (1) is
  true, it would suggest that the area west of Singleton may have been
  trilingual, with speakers of Wiradjuri, HRLM and Gamilaraay all
  frequently present. If hypotheses (2) and/or (3) are true, this would
  be consistent with Lissarrague’s surmise that the area west of
  Singleton was a transitional zone between HRLM and Gamilaraay. These
  hypotheses are hard to adjudicate, given the lack of corroborating
  evidence, but all are consistent with the general impression that
  Harpur learned most of his Indigenous vocabulary directly from local
  Indigenous informants in the 1830s and 40s.</p>
  <p>While the <italic>facts</italic> of the case are murky, the
  <italic>poetics</italic> are clear. In sharp distinction to Dunlop,
  Harpur presents each word as a particular word spoken by particular
  people in a particular place. “Jimbuc” and “whirring” are only the
  most obvious instances. Consider these lines from Part II, when Harpur
  describes the sunrise:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Uncovered no longer the forest dog prowls,
    Though so bold in the dark;
    And the kindynef and bidawongg haste to their holes
    In the spouts of yon old ironbark:
    While on its one bare blasted limb
    The gooburrah sits in the fog-wreath dim,
    Glorying loud with a laughter-like glee
    In the march of the dayspring’s victory […] (h209-cf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In each footnote, Harpur identifies the word as “an Aboriginal
  name”, emphasising the indefinite article in footnote
  <italic>g</italic>: “I say <italic>an</italic> aboriginal name,
  because almost every tribe of Blacks has a different set of names for
  our indiginous animals.” (h209-cf) His precision about language is
  linked to his precision about nature. He places each animal in its
  ecological niche: the dog’s hunting patterns change in the daytime,
  the “bidawong” (glider) and “kindyne” (ring-tailed possum) nest
  specifically in the “ironbark,” and the kookaburra sits on a “bare”
  branch where it can see its prey. Dixon
  (<xref alt="1980, 322" rid="ref-dixon_charles_1980" ref-type="bibr">1980,
  322</xref>) compares the poem to a “natural history painting,” which
  presents a “typical and comprehensive cross section of the forest
  environment.” Natural history provides a ground-truth for Harpur’s
  analysis of names. Each animal or plant can be classified by species,
  then an appropriate name for the species can be selected from colonial
  English or local Indigenous languages. In one case, Harpur invents his
  <italic>own</italic> word for a species, having failed to locate an
  appropriate name. His invented name for the eastern whip-bird, “Jehu,”
  alludes to the bird’s colonial nickname of “coachman’s whip” (h209-gf,
  note d).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref></p>
  <p>Harpur chooses Indigenous names because they are more “poetic.” For
  instance, to justify the choice of “gooburra” as a name for the
  kookaburra, he sarcastically dismisses the “the tasteful and poetic
  sobriquet of the Laughing Jackass” conferred on the bird by white
  settlers (h209-cf). His discussion of Indigenous names is most
  pregnant in the case of “Euroka,” which he invokes in Part I of the
  poem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Or while Eurokab first displays
    His burning rim on the ancient hill,
    […]
    He floods abroad his golden light
    In one unbroken mass immense
    Of life-essential influence […]
    b Euroka is an aboriginal name of the sun. It is at once euphonious
    and robust, and has therefore a certain sounding adequacy as a
    vocable, and thence somewhat of ideal unison with the golden
    progression and godlike port of that paramount luminary.
    (h209-bf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Harpur makes two claims for “Euroka.” First, the word itself is
  “euphonious and robust” as a “vocable.” Second, the word’s euphony
  means it can achieve an “ideal unison” with the reality it
  denotes—namely, the sun. For Harpur, the “ideality” of poetry arises
  from the unification of word and
  world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref> To idealise the world,
  the poet must see each particular thing correctly, and then the select
  the word that will communicate that particularity. Harpur thus makes a
  strong claim for Indigenous poetics. Twelve times in <italic>The
  Kangaroo Hunt</italic>, Harpur claims that Indigenous people have
  properly seen the world, and found the ideal word to communicate what
  they have seen
  (<xref alt="Webby 2013, 5" rid="ref-webby_representations_2013" ref-type="bibr">Webby
  2013, 5</xref>). In the case of Euroka, Harpur emphasises the point by
  using Euroka himself as a symbol of ideality. Euroka illuminates the
  earth, uniting all things in the “one unbroken mass” of his
  “life-essential influence.”</p>
  <p>Harpur observes Euroka rise, but does not actually invoke him as
  the muse. Instead, Harpur compares himself to Euroka: as Euroka rises
  to illuminate the world, so the poet walks to the top of a hill to
  survey the scene. At this point in the poem, its troubling colonial
  elements come into view:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>While thus Euroka riseth red,
    Up, even to the kingly head
    Of some proud eminence, we climb,
    Where high amid the crags sublime,
    Australia’s yet unchristened Muse,
    A wandering Spirit of beauty rare,
    Loves oft to gem her streaming hair
    With heaven’s selectest dews,
    And scarf her bosom bright and bare
    With a robe of Morning richest hues;
    Giving the while to all objects there,
    All sounds,—the water drip just heard—
    The hum of insect—voice of bird,—
    To every echo and every air
    A poetry unfelt elsewhere. (h209-bf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In this image, Harpur illuminates the world with the ideal beauty
  of poetry, just as Euroka illuminates the world with his light. But
  the introduction of “Australia’s yet unchristened Muse” complicates
  things. What does “unchristened” mean? Does it mean that the Muse is
  unnamed, or simply that she has not “yet” been named by the Christian
  settlers? In either case, what is the significance of her naming?
  Harpur defends Indigenous speech as “euphonious” and “poetic.” He
  suggests that the poetry of the forest can be seen in the “dew,” heard
  in “All sounds,” and “felt” in the air. He suggests that the Muse is
  solar-powered, as Euroka “robes” her in beauty. Harpur himself
  refrains from naming the Muse in this very poem where he foreshadows
  her “christening.” Does all this mean that the Muse of Australia is
  eternal, and freely available to any human being to happens to walk in
  her domain? Or, more darkly, does Harpur propose that the white
  settlers will one day expropriate the Muse from the first Australians,
  by “christening” her? Harpur does not resolve these issues.
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> is a poem of futurity, and Harpur
  looks forward to a time when the poem’s own questions may be
  answered.</p>
  <p>In the final lines of the poem, however, Harpur does recur to the
  Muse. In these lines, Harpur describes himself as an “uncouth” poet,
  and apologises for his lack of education. He then aligns his own
  “uncouthness” with the “virginity” of the Muse:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Thus nurtured,—self urged, first he knew
    Australia’s virgin Muse to woo,
    And of Song’s bright mysteries ’gan to guess
    With a lone self-cherished studiousness […] (h209-gf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Again the imagery is ambiguous. Does the virginity of the Muse
  imply that one day, she will marry the white settlers? Or does it
  imply that she is <italic>always</italic> a virgin, and that the
  poetry of Australia truly belongs to no-one, neither settler nor
  Indigenous? Harpur forecloses a third possibility, that the Muse was
  already married when the white settlers came. He is anxious to secure
  his poetic authority. Without the benefit of education, he claims
  authority from his connection to the land. But he realises full well
  that Indigenous Australians already have this connection. In Part III,
  Harpur acknowledges Indigenous Australians as “the former lords of the
  soil.” He praises their wise husbandry, which prevented the mass
  “extinction” of native birds brought about by white settlement
  (h209-df, note e). The wise husbandry and poetic speech of Indigenous
  Australians are both a problem and a solution for Harpur. Indigenous
  Australians have proven there is an Australian poetry inherent in the
  land, but they also threaten the white settler’s right to compose that
  poetry. The unnamed, unmarried “Muse of Australia” is Harpur’s attempt
  to resolve this contradiction.</p>
  <p>Where Dunlop’s translation is smooth and familiar, Harpur’s epic is
  craggy and difficult. He enjoins the reader to pause on each word,
  each image, and appreciate its robustness. Thus in the poem’s
  <italic>language</italic> as well as its plot, Harpur dramatises the
  struggle to comprehend the Australian environment. This struggle
  reflects broader themes in Harpur’s work: his struggle to cement his
  authority as the colony’s “first” poet
  (<xref alt="Mead 1990" rid="ref-mead_charles_1990" ref-type="bibr">Mead
  1990</xref>); and his interest in the struggle between “nature and
  intellect” in cognition
  (<xref alt="Ackland 1983, 460" rid="ref-ackland_charles_1983" ref-type="bibr">Ackland
  1983, 460</xref>). Harpur adopts particular Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and
  HRLM words whose sound and meaning allows him to comprehend the
  landscape more fully. This is why I say his representation of
  Indigenous language is <italic>verbal</italic> and
  <italic>oral</italic>—he sees language as a collection of
  <italic>words</italic> that are <italic>spoken</italic> to denote
  particular things.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="linguistic-representation-and-the-conquest-of-space">
  <title>4 Linguistic representation and the conquest of space</title>
  <p>Both Dunlop and Harpur claim poetic authority, and seek to write an
  Australian poetry which somehow reconciles the rights of white
  settlers and Indigenous Australians. In both cases, however, the white
  poet asserts the right to choose: to open the pantry of Indigenous
  poetry, and select the choicest morsels for their own compositions.
  Today this might be condemned as cultural appropriation
  (<xref alt="O’Leary 2004, 85" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004" ref-type="bibr">O’Leary
  2004, 85</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston 2021, 47" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 47</xref>), but neither Dunlop nor Harpur seem to have been
  concerned that linguistic “borrowings” could be a kind of theft. It
  was simply obvious to Harpur and Dunlop that words don’t belong to
  anybody. Why not? In this section, I sketch the linguistic philosphy
  that justified their attitudes.</p>
  <p>In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, the empiricist philosophy of language
  predominated in the English-speaking world. Dunlop was well-versed in
  British empiricism, having read David Hume by the age of 12
  (<xref alt="Hansord 2021, 76" rid="ref-hansord_imperial_2021" ref-type="bibr">Hansord
  2021, 76</xref>). Harpur’s education is not well attested, but he was
  a close reader of Percy Shelley, whose debts to radical empiricism are
  well known.</p>
  <p>In the empiricist theory of language, language is made up of
  “signs,” and these “signs” are simply labels that we apply to objects
  we perceive
  (<xref alt="Bergheaud 1985, 159" rid="ref-bergheaud_empiricism_1985" ref-type="bibr">Bergheaud
  1985, 159</xref>). As Locke
  (<xref alt="1975, 405" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  405</xref>) argues, signs are arbitrary: words become signs for our
  ideas through “voluntary imposition.” Initially, we label “simple
  ideas,” such as <italic>red</italic>, <italic>wood</italic> or
  <italic>water</italic>. Later, we stitch together simple ideas to
  build up “complex ideas,” and label these complex ideas with signs
  such as <italic>government</italic> or <italic>religion</italic>
  (<xref alt="1975, sec. 3.2" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  sec. 3.2</xref>). Locke’s view is psychological and individualistic.
  My perceptual system delivers sensations into my mind, and I choose to
  label them with other sensations, namely sounds and visible
  characters, which then become signs. Locke was accordingly sceptical
  of abstract concepts. Ultimately a word is only meaningful if it can
  be reduced to simple, perceptible ideas such as <italic>hard</italic>
  or <italic>round</italic>. But when we use abstract words such as
  <italic>power</italic>, it is easy to forget the complex of particular
  sensations that the word refers to. Thus we often “have very good and
  approved Words in [our] Mouths, and Writings, with very uncertain,
  little or no signification”
  (<xref alt="1975, 438" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  438</xref>).</p>
  <p>In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, the most famous proponent of Locke’s
  ideas was John Horne Tooke
  (<xref alt="Aarsleff 1967, chap. 2" rid="ref-aarsleff_study_1967" ref-type="bibr">Aarsleff
  1967, chap. 2</xref>). Tooke
  (<xref alt="1805, vol. 1" rid="ref-tooke_epea_1805" ref-type="bibr">1805,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 18) begins with the proposition that “Words are the
  <italic>signs</italic> of <italic>things</italic>,” and then poses a
  difficult problem: there are many words, such as prepositions and
  articles, which do not refer to perceptible things. You cannot smell
  <italic>an</italic> or touch <italic>of</italic>. To save the
  empiricist theory of language, he attempts to prove that words such as
  <italic>an</italic> or <italic>of</italic> are “abbrevations” of nouns
  and verbs, offering some very inventive etymologies to illustrate his
  theory. He justifies the theory by observing that the human mind has
  an innate love of “<italic>dispatch</italic>”
  (<xref alt="1805, vol. 1" rid="ref-tooke_epea_1805" ref-type="bibr">1805,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 27). We wish to speak quickly, therefore we
  abbreviate, and generate all the abstract words of a fully
  grammaticizised language. Tooke’s ideas were later promulgated by the
  utilitarians, who in turn influenced the young Tennyson and Browning
  (<xref alt="Cooper 2006, 642–43" rid="ref-cooper_womens_2006" ref-type="bibr">Cooper
  2006, 642–43</xref>). In his posthumous writings on language, Jeremy
  Bentham
  (<xref alt="1843" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843" ref-type="bibr">1843</xref>)
  argues that every “sign” in language stands for some “entity,” and
  distinguishes “real” from “fictitious” entities. A “real” entity is
  “an object, the existence of which is made known to us by one or more
  of our five senses”; a “fictitious” entity is “an object, the
  existence of which is feigned by the imagination”
  (<xref alt="1843, 325" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843" ref-type="bibr">1843,
  325</xref>). A word denoting a “fictitious” entity can only be
  meaningful if the fictitious entity can be broken down into real,
  perceptible entities: to every word with an “immaterial import there
  belongs, or at least did belong, a material one”
  (<xref alt="1843, 329" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843" ref-type="bibr">1843,
  329</xref>). For Tooke, Bentham, and their empiricist forebears, human
  language is universal. Everywhere the operations of the mind are the
  same. Everywhere the mind encounters the same kind of material things.
  Since words are names for things, I can always understand the meaning
  of a word by learning what things it refers to, even when the word
  seems to denote an abstract concept.</p>
  <p>This analysis reveals that Dunlop’s universalism and Harpur’s
  particularism are two sides of the same coin. Harpur’s particularism
  would be impossible without the universality of the mind. Dunlop’s
  universality would be impossible without the particularity of the
  senses. Harpur asserts the universality of the human mind in mystical
  poems such as <italic>The Tower of the Dream</italic> (1851-53, h642a)
  and <italic>Cosmoplasticus</italic> (1857, h696c). In the major work
  of his maturity, <italic>The Witch of Hebron</italic> (1867, h689-gd),
  he suggests that each person originates alike in an “aboriginal
  inception, / […] A self-producing knot of living
  shoots[.]”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref> Thus Harpur’s
  particularism has a universalist substrate. By contrast, Dunlop’s
  universalism expresses itself in particularism. We have already seen
  how she amplifies Wulatji’s text with sensory images, explicitly
  evoking the sounds, sights and feelings that Wulatji himself leaves
  implicit. In other poems, she describes particular places in loving
  detail, as in this stanza on her home at Mulla Villa:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>    Deep, silent water—water dark and still,
        Bowered in the desert, lonely lot is thine!
        For thee, no courtly Bard, essays his skill
    At thy cool font inspired—“sweet Mulla mine.”
    (<xref alt="Dunlop 2021, 198" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    2021, 198</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In this stanza, she evokes the sights and sounds of her home
  (“silent water—water dark”) in order to particularise it: her “Mulla,”
  the creek behind her home, is <italic>not</italic> the “Mulla” where
  the “courtly bard” Edmund Spenser lived in the sixteenth century.</p>
  <p>Harpur is traditionally labelled “Romantic” (e.g. by
  <xref alt="Kane 1996" rid="ref-kane_australian_1996" ref-type="bibr">Kane
  1996</xref>;
  <xref alt="Kelly and Fotheringham 1987" rid="ref-harpur_general_1987" ref-type="bibr">Kelly
  and Fotheringham 1987</xref>), while his female contemporaries such as
  Dunlop are labelled “sentimental.” Harpur and Dunlop’s shared
  empiricism, however, suggests that this distinction is illusory. Like
  earlier Romantics, such as Samuel Taylor Coleridge or Felicia Hemans,
  both Harpur and Dunlop seek the “One Mind” that is immanent in
  experience. Wu
  (<xref alt="2021, 69" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021" ref-type="bibr">2021,
  69</xref>) is therefore quite correct when he writes: “Dunlop realised
  as clearly as any of the Romantic poets that art lives in the realm of
  the ideal” (see also
  <xref alt="Minter 2021, 109" rid="ref-minter_settlement_2021" ref-type="bibr">Minter
  2021, 109</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hansord 2021, 79" rid="ref-hansord_imperial_2021" ref-type="bibr">Hansord
  2021, 79</xref>).</p>
  <p>What does Dunlop and Harpur’s empiricism have to do with the
  ownership of words? We can answer this question by comparing the
  then-dominant English theory of language with the then-dominant German
  theory. In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, German scholars had rejected the
  tradition of “philosophical grammar” represented by Locke, Tooke and
  Bentham, and were pursuing the new discipline of “historical
  philology”
  (<xref alt="Foucault 2002, xii" rid="ref-foucault_order_2002" ref-type="bibr">Foucault
  2002, xii</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aarsleff 1967, 3–6" rid="ref-aarsleff_study_1967" ref-type="bibr">Aarsleff
  1967, 3–6</xref>). In historical philology, the sign is no longer an
  arbitrary label for a sensation. Instead, words themselves are objects
  that have their own histories, can they cannot simply be detached from
  the languages of which they form a part. As Foucault
  (<xref alt="2002, 256" rid="ref-foucault_order_2002" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  256</xref>) puts it, in historical philology, language has an
  “interior ‘mechanism’” that determines the distribution and
  interrelations of words. If this is the case, then linguistic
  borrowing becomes problematic. One of the early proponents of
  historical philology, Johann Gottfried Herder
  (<xref alt="1993, 38–39" rid="ref-herder_against_1993" ref-type="bibr">1993,
  38–39</xref>) illustrates the problem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>You must first enter the spirit of a nation in order to empathize
    completely with even one of its thoughts or deeds. You must discover
    a characterizing word through which you can understand everything in
    depth. Otherwise, you simply read a word.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>A word is not a name applied by an individual to a sensation; it is
  the expression of the “spirit of a nation.” If you do not know this
  “spirit,” you do not “understand” the word, you simply “read” it.
  Herder’s argument invalidates Dunlop’s procedure of swapping one word
  for another in her translation: “bato” (<italic>paTu</italic>) cannot
  translate “kokein” (<italic>kukuyn</italic>): these are different
  words, even if they refer to the same object of perception. Herder’s
  argument also invalidates Harpur’s procedure of selecting words for
  their “euphoniousness:” Harpur has merely “read” the word for its
  sounds, rather than grasping its spirit.</p>
  <p>One implication of historical philology is that human nature
  changes. Human nature is “a pliant clay, which assumes different
  shapes under different circumstances, needs, and burdens”
  (<xref alt="Herder 1993, 43" rid="ref-herder_against_1993" ref-type="bibr">Herder
  1993, 43</xref>). This view of human nature undermines the
  metaphysical presuppositions of Harpur and Dunlop’s poetry. There is
  no one mind that expresses itself in song, as Dunlop believed. We do
  not live in a shared world of particulars that guarantee the meaning
  of words, as Harpur believed. Herder and the historicists could not
  endorse Dunlop and Harpur’s programme.</p>
  <p>This analysis indicates precisely why it is anachronistic to accuse
  Harpur and Dunlop of “cultural appropriation.” In their view, words
  were labels for perceptions, and it was open to any person at any time
  to invent or adopt a new
  label.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref> Since words do not
  belong to a “culture,” they cannot be stolen from one. When Dunlop and
  Harpur conquered space, they did not do so by stealing its names, but
  by enriching the English language so its speakers could name
  Australia. To enrich the English language, they produced
  representations of Indigenous language: a transcription, a
  translation, a glossary, and philological footnotes. This does not
  absolve them of imperial ambition. When they named Australia, they
  helped to take the things they named, even if they did not mean to
  take the names themselves.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusion-agony">
  <title>5 Conclusion: Agony</title>
  <p>Dunlop and Harpur make themselves at home in Australia only in an
  agony of conscience. Other colonial poets were not so agonised. Emily
  Manning
  (<xref alt="1877, 43" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877" ref-type="bibr">1877,
  43</xref>), for example, ends her otherwise beautiful poem “From the
  Clyde to Braidwood” on this dismissive note:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>            —no legend old
    Adds softening beauty to the Buddawong Peak,
    Or near home-ranges with too barbarous names.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Manning can read no “legend” in the landscape, and dismisses the
  local names of the Braidwood district as “barbarous”—even though she
  uses three Indigenous Australian words in the poem, namely
  “Currawong,” “Kurrajong” and (in these very lines) “Buddawong.” She
  describes the road from Clyde to Braidwood in wonderful detail, but
  the only human activity she can see there is the activity of the white
  man who has “cleft the rock” to build the road
  (<xref alt="Manning 1877, 42" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877" ref-type="bibr">Manning
  1877, 42</xref>). The poem is a mature expression of a Australian
  tradition inaugrated by Barron Field, who established in both law and
  poetry the doctrine of <italic>terra nullius</italic>
  (<xref alt="Ford and Clemens 2023" rid="ref-ford_barron_2023" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  and Clemens 2023</xref>). To Manning’s eyes, the land is empty, its
  past is untold, and if it has names, they are “barbarous.” Braidwood
  itself is therefore “new, new, too new / To foster Poesy”
  (<xref alt="Manning 1877, 43" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877" ref-type="bibr">Manning
  1877, 43</xref>).</p>
  <p>Neither Harpur nor Dunlop were members of this tradition. Both
  found poetry in the Australian landscape, and acknowledged that
  Indigenous Australians had found it first. They attempted to convey
  this poetry to colonial readers by setting forth the riches of
  Indigenous speech and writing. Dunlop presented Wulatji as a bard in
  the tradition of world poetry, and treated Awabakal (HRLM) as a
  classical language of civilisation. Harpur presented his Darkinyung,
  Gamilaraay and Wonnarua informants as skilled workers of the land, who
  had seen and named myriad beauties of the world. Though Dunlop and
  Harpur adopted different means to represent Indigenous languages,
  their underlying philosophy was similar, as was their agony, which was
  to “[reinscribe] the logic of colonisation” in the face of its
  injustice
  (<xref alt="Minter 2021, 113" rid="ref-minter_settlement_2021" ref-type="bibr">Minter
  2021, 113</xref>). They wrote vexed and contradictory poetry, whose
  vexation has lost none of its pertinence in the third century of
  Australia’s colonisation.</p>
  <p>Wulatji, meanwhile, can speak for himself.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>6 Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I am grateful to Jim Wafer and Grace Karskens for sharing their
  unpublished notes on Harpur’s <italic>Kangaroo Hunt</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-wulatji_native_1848">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Wulatji</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Native Poetry</article-title>
      <source>The Sydney Morning Herald</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1848-10">1848</year><month>10</month>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article12904464</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dixon_australian_2006">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Bruce</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ramson</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Mandy</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Australian Aboriginal Words in English: Their Origin and Meaning</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      <edition>Second Edition</edition>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-falk_endless_2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Endless Forms of Things: Harpur’s Radicalism Revisited</article-title>
      <source>Journal of the Association for the Study of Australian Literature</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-02">2019</year><month>02</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-09-24">2019</year><month>09</month><day>24</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>18</issue>
      <issn>1833-6027</issn>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/index.php/JASAL/article/view/13026</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ackland_charles_1983">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ackland</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur’s &quot;the bush fire&quot; and &quot;a storm in the mountains&quot;: Sublimity, cognition and faith</article-title>
      <source>Southerly</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1983-12">1983</year><month>12</month>
      <volume>43</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <issn>0038-3732</issn>
      <fpage>459</fpage>
      <lpage>474</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-aarsleff_study_1967">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Aarsleff</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Study of Language in England, 1780-1860</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1967">1967</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dixon_charles_1980">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur and John Gould</article-title>
      <source>Southerly</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1980-09">1980</year><month>09</month>
      <volume>40</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>0038-3732</issn>
      <fpage>315</fpage>
      <lpage>329</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-mead_charles_1990">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur’s Disfiguring Origins: Allegory in Colonial Poetry</article-title>
      <source>Australian Literary Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>279</fpage>
      <lpage>296</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-kane_australian_1996">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Australian Poetry: Romanticism and Negativity</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-locke_essay_1975">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Nidditch</surname><given-names>Peter H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-van_toorn_terrors_1992">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Van Toorn</surname><given-names>Penny</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Terrors of Terra Nullius: Gothicising and De‐Gothicising aboriginality</article-title>
      <source>World Literature Written in English</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
      <volume>32</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17449859208589194</pub-id>
      <fpage>87</fpage>
      <lpage>97</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-troy_sydney_1993">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>Jakelin</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Sydney Language</source>
      <publisher-name>Jakelin Troy</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-oleary_giving_2004">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Giving the indigenous a voice — further thoughts on the poetry of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Australian Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2004-01">2004</year><month>01</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-07-16">2019</year><month>07</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>28</volume>
      <issue>82</issue>
      <issn>1444-3058</issn>
      <uri>https://doi.org/10.1080/14443050409387958</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14443050409387958</pub-id>
      <fpage>85</fpage>
      <lpage>93</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Lissarrague</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>A salvage grammar and wordlist of the language from the Hunter River and Lake Macquarie</source>
      <publisher-name>Muurrbay Aboriginal Language; Culture Cooperative</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Nambucca Heads, NSW</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      <isbn>978-0-9775351-0-1</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-foucault_order_2002">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Order of Things: An Archaeology of the Human Sciences</source>
      <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_general_1987">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Veronica</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fotheringham</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>General Editors’ Preface</article-title>
      <source>Stalwart the Bushranger, with The Tragedy of Donohoe</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Currency Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year>
      <fpage>vi</fpage>
      <lpage>x</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-eggert_charles_2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Eggert</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur: The Editorial Nightmare</article-title>
      <source>JASAL</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/JASAL/article/view/11011</uri>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>14</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-webby_representations_2013">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Representations of ’The Bush’ in the Poetry of Charles Harpur</article-title>
      <source>JASAL</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/JASAL/article/view/10266</uri>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>8</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_charles_2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harpur</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Charles Harpur Critical Archive</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Eggert</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-683-1</isbn>
      <uri>http://charles-harpur.org/</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-carter_road_2010">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The road to Botany Bay: An exploration of landscape and history</source>
      <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <isbn>978-0-8166-6997-4</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wafer</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Ghost-writing for Wulatji: Incubation and re-dreaming as song revitalisation practices</article-title>
      <source>Recirculating Songs: Revitalising the singing practices of Indigenous Australia</source>
      <publisher-name>Hunter Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Newcastle</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-07">2020</year><month>01</month><day>07</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>https://openresearch-repository.anu.edu.au/bitstream/1885/132161/18/9_wafer.pdf</uri>
      <fpage>193</fpage>
      <lpage>256</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
        <string-name>Wulatji</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Pialla Wollombi</article-title>
      <source>The Southern Euphrosyne and Australian Miscellany: Containing oriental moral takes, original anecdote, poetry and music</source>
      <publisher-name>Whittaker &amp; Co.</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London; Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1848">1848</year>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-166023361</uri>
      <fpage>94</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-tuan_space_1977">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>Yi-Fu</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Space and Place: The Perspective of Experience</source>
      <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1977">1977</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-gelder_colonial_2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gelder</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>Rachael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Colonial Kangaroo Hunt</source>
      <publisher-name>Melbourne University Publishing</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-06">2024</year><month>05</month><day>06</day></date-in-citation>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-0-522-87586-7</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_selection_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A Selection of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop’s Poems</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>175</fpage>
      <lpage>204</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-johnston_proud_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>“Proud of Contributing Its Quota to the Original Literature of the Colony” : An Introduction to Eliza Hamilton Dunlop and Her Writing</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>8</fpage>
      <lpage>30</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wafer_unmapping_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wafer</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Unmapping the Mulla : Dunlop and the Villa on Wollombi Brook</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>154</fpage>
      <lpage>173</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-minter_settlement_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Minter</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Settlement Defiled : Ventriloquy, Pollution and Nature in Eliza Hamilton Dunlops’ ’The Aboriginal Mother’</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>103</fpage>
      <lpage>115</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-rudy_beyond_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>Jason R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Beyond Universalisms : Individuation, Race and Sentiment in Colonial New South Wales</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>91</fpage>
      <lpage>101</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-hansord_imperial_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Hansord</surname><given-names>Katrina</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Imperial Feminism and “My Father’s Library” : Intellectual, Literary and Political Thought in Eliza Hamilton Dunlop’s Poetry</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>74</fpage>
      <lpage>90</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wu_morning_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Duncan</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>“Morning on Rostrevor Mountains” and the Making of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>56</fpage>
      <lpage>73</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-johnston_poetry_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Poetry of the Archive : Locating Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>30</fpage>
      <lpage>54</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_australian_1843">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harpur</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Australian Scenery (From the &quot;Kangaroo Hunt,&quot; an unpublished poem)</article-title>
      <source>Weekly Register of Politics, Facts and General Literature</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1843-11">1843</year><month>11</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-08">2024</year><month>05</month><day>08</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article228135900</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <source>Gamilaraay, Yuwaalaraay &amp; Yuwaalayaay dictionary</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Lissarrague</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Giacon</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>IAD Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Alice Springs, N.T</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <isbn>978-1-86465-051-8</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ellis_dhurga_2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <source>The Dhurga dictionary and learner’s grammar: A south-east coast, NSW Aboriginal language</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Boyenga</surname><given-names>Kerry</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>Waine</given-names></name>
        <string-name>Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Aboriginal Studies Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Canberra, ACT</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <edition>1st</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-925302-60-8</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Darkinyung grammar and dictionary: Revitalising a language from historical sources</source>
      <publisher-name>Muurrbay Aboriginal Language; Culture Co-operative</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Nambucca Heads, N.S.W</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
      <isbn>978-0-9775351-9-4</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-grant_new_2010">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Stan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Stan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rudder</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>A new Wiradjuri dictionary</source>
      <publisher-name>Restoration House</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>O’Connor, A.C.T</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <isbn>978-0-86942-150-5</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Poesy</article-title>
      <source>Australian Town and Country Journal</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, NSW</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1872-10">1872</year><month>10</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-11-03">2020</year><month>11</month><day>03</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article70497610</uri>
      <fpage>20</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-cooper_womens_2006">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Andrew R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Women’s Poetry, the 1830s, and Monumental Problems in the History of Language Theory.</article-title>
      <source>Women’s Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006-10">2006</year><month>10</month>
      <volume>35</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <issn>0049-7878</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00497870600904144</pub-id>
      <fpage>621</fpage>
      <lpage>655</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-bergheaud_empiricism_1985">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bergheaud</surname><given-names>Patrice</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Empiricism and linguistics in eighteenth-century Great Britain</article-title>
      <source>Topoi</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1985-09">1985</year><month>09</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-15">2024</year><month>05</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <issn>0167-7411, 1572-8749</issn>
      <uri>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/BF00135843</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00135843</pub-id>
      <fpage>155</fpage>
      <lpage>163</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-tooke_epea_1805">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tooke</surname><given-names>John Horne</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Epea pteroenta. Or, the diversions of Purley</source>
      <publisher-name>J. Johnson</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1805">1805</year>
      <edition>Second Edition</edition>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_vase_nodate">
    <element-citation publication-type="manuscript">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Vase, comprising songs for music and poems</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>State Library of New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <uri>https://collection.sl.nsw.gov.au/record/Yold2BN9</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_mind_1872">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Mind</article-title>
      <source>Evening News</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1872-06">1872</year><month>06</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-15">2024</year><month>05</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article114733889</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-geoscience_australia_geodata_2003">
    <element-citation>
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Geoscience Australia</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>GEODATA TOPO 2.5M</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <uri>https://pid.geoscience.gov.au/dataset/ga/60804</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-bentham_essay_1843">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bentham</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Essay on Language</article-title>
      <source>The works of Jeremy Bentham</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Bowring</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>W. Tait</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1843">1843</year>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <edition>1st</edition>
      <fpage>294</fpage>
      <lpage>357</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-herder_against_1993">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Herder</surname><given-names>Johann Gottfried von</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Against pure reason: Writings on religion, language, and history</source>
      <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
      <isbn>978-0-8006-3212-0</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-manning_balance_1877">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The balance of pain : And other poems</source>
      <publisher-name>London: G. Bell</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1877">1877</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-20">2024</year><month>05</month><day>20</day></date-in-citation>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ford_barron_2023">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>Thomas H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Barron field in New South Wales: The poetics of Terra Nullius</source>
      <publisher-name>Melbourne University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Carlton, Victoria</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year>
      <isbn>978-0-522-87878-3</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
    <label>1</label><p>She later adapted the poem for Isaac Nathan’s
    song collection, <italic>The Southern Euphrosyne</italic>
    (<xref alt="Dunlop and Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    and Wulatji 1848</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn2">
    <label>2</label><p>Paul Eggert’s variorum edition of Harpur’s poetry
    provides an ‘h-number’ for each version of each poem. I refer to
    Harpur’s poems by h-number throughout. Each of <italic>Kangaroo
    Hunt</italic>’s six parts has its own h-number.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn3">
    <label>3</label><p>In another poem of the same year, she extols the
    universality of “IMPERIAL MIND!”, which compels “Obedience”
    throughout its “boundless realm”
    (<xref alt="1872a" rid="ref-dunlop_mind_1872" ref-type="bibr">1872a</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn4">
    <label>4</label><p>Her brothers were not so friendly. They refused
    to acknowledge their Indian half-sisters, and denied them their
    inheritance
    (<xref alt="Johnston 2021, 39" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
    2021, 39</xref>;
    <xref alt="Wu 2021, 63" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021" ref-type="bibr">Wu
    2021, 63</xref>)</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn5">
    <label>5</label><p>According to Threlkeld, Wulatji was a popular
    guest, whose humourous ‘gibes’ and ‘song and dance’ routines were
    highly appreciated by Indigenous people throughout the region
    (quoted in
    <xref alt="Wafer 2017, 200" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">Wafer
    2017, 200</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn6">
    <label>6</label><p>On the coincidence between Wulatji’s name and
    Wallatu’s, see O’Leary
    (<xref alt="2004, 91" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004" ref-type="bibr">2004,
    91</xref>) and Wafer
    (<xref alt="2017, 199" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017,
    199</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn7">
    <label>7</label><p>I am indebted to Jim Wafer for sharing his notes
    on Harpur’s Indigenous vocabulary, which helped especially with the
    difficult <italic>teleltella</italic>.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn8">
    <label>8</label><p>Harpur’s name never caught on, although Henry
    Kendall borrowed it for his own kangaroo hunt poem. Kendall was
    apparently unaware the “Jehu” is a colloquial term for a coachman,
    and changed the spelling to “echu,” emphasising its onomatopoeia
    (<xref alt="Gelder and Weaver 2020, 73" rid="ref-gelder_colonial_2020" ref-type="bibr">Gelder
    and Weaver 2020, 73</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn9">
    <label>9</label><p>The word is Harpur’s. See for instance h185b.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn10">
    <label>10</label><p>This image does suggest a “developmental”
    viewpoint that is superficially similar to Herder’s historicism; but
    Harpur’s view of development was more teleological that Herder’s
    (<xref alt="Falk 2019, 6–10" rid="ref-falk_endless_2019" ref-type="bibr">Falk
    2019, 6–10</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn11">
    <label>11</label><p>How Wulatji and other Indigenous informants
    viewed these linguistic “borrowings” I do not know.</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>

<sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-4-nb-article">
<front-stub>
<title-group>
<article-title>Land and Language in Australian
Romanticism</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9261-8390</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Falk</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Michael Falk</string-name>

<email>michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1-nb-article">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1-nb-article">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Melbourne</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1-nb-article">michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</corresp>
</author-notes>
<abstract>
Eliza Hamilton Dunlop (1796-1880) and Charles Harpur (1813-1867) were
two of the most important Romantic poets of colonial New South Wales. In
this article, I consider their engagement with Indigenous Australian
languages. In ‘Native Song’ (1848), Dunlop provides a transcription and
translation of verse composed by her informant Wulatji (fl. 1840s), a
famous Awabakal poet. In <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> (c. 1844),
Harpur enriches his description of Australian landscapes with a dozen
words learned from Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and Wonnarua informants. I
contrast Dunlop’s universalist approach to Indigenous langauge with
Harpur’s particularist approach, and contextualise their poetry in
British philosophy of language. Dunlop and Harpur use Indigenous
language to present Australia as a land steeped in poetry, but their
recognition of Indigenous poetry undermines their own attempts to make
themselves at home in the colony.
</abstract>
</front-stub>

<body>
<sec id="nb-code-cell-1-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
<code language="r script"># Setup cell
knitr::opts_chunk$set(echo = FALSE)
options(knitr.kable.NA = '')

DATA_DIR &lt;- &quot;data&quot;
harpur &lt;- file.path(DATA_DIR, &quot;harpur-lang.xlsx&quot;) |&gt; readxl::read_xlsx()
dunlop &lt;- file.path(DATA_DIR, &quot;dunlop-lang.xlsx&quot;) |&gt; readxl::read_xlsx()</code>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction-nb-article">
  <title>1 Introduction</title>
  <p>To occupy Australia, its European invaders had to name it. This was
  not merely a matter of naming places, though that of course was
  crucial. They also needed to name the things that made the places.
  They needed to name the trees that dropped their autumn bark, the
  deer-like creatures that hopped on two legs, the fires that ripped
  through crackling scrubland. They needed to name the fickle weather,
  the whirling dust, the intermittent streams. They needed to name
  hundreds of parrots and pigeons and snakes and dragons. They needed to
  name the people from whom they took the land. To conquer Australia,
  they “conquered space.” With a touch of the namer’s wand, they changed
  a strange land “into a familiar world of routes and places”
  (<xref alt="Tuan 1977, 83" rid="ref-tuan_space_1977-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Tuan
  1977, 83</xref>).</p>
  <p>The invaders mined Indigenous languages for names. Indigenous names
  had the advantage of establishment. The Indigenous name is the “real
  and proper” name, thought Lachlan Macquarie (quoted in
  <xref alt="Carter 2010, 328" rid="ref-carter_road_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Carter
  2010, 328</xref>). But what the invaders found “real and proper” was
  not always what the conquered found “real and proper.” In Australia,
  the Europeans debased words such as <italic>gin</italic> and
  <italic>lubra</italic>, while mixing myriad other words from myriad
  tongues into the new Australian English.</p>
  <p>In the 1840s, two invader-poets observed this situation and
  attempted to rectify it. Eliza Hamilton Dunlop and Charles Harpur were
  humanitarians who recognised the value of Indigenous poetry. They
  praised Indigenous Australian languages, and borrowed Indigenous words
  to enrich their poetic diction. Thus they attempted to conquer space
  and make themselves at home, while also recognising the prior claims
  of Indigenous Australians to the land.</p>
  <p>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop (1796-1880) was the Irish wife of the
  Protector of Aborigines in Wollombi (see
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-map-nb-article">Figure 1</xref>). She befriended a
  local poet, Wulatji (fl. 1840s), learned his tongue, and published a
  transcription and translation of his poetry in the <italic>Sydney
  Morning Herald</italic>
  (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
  1848</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-nb-article">1</xref> Twenty-first
  century critics have praised Dunlop’s appreciation for Indigenous
  cultures, while noting her “colonialism” and “cultural appropriation”
  by more recent standards
  (<xref alt="O’Leary 2004" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">O’Leary
  2004</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston 2021, 47" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 47</xref>). Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  has verified the accuracy of her translation, and used it to
  reconstruct Wulatji’s song-writing practices. He also highlights a
  remarkable fact about Dunlop’s translation, which has hitherto escaped
  literary analysis: she translates many of Wulatji’s words by
  <italic>other</italic> Indigenous words, often from far-flung
  languages.</p>
  <p>Charles Harpur (1813-1867) was a currency lad, born to convict
  parents on the banks of Deerubbin (the Hawkesbury-Nepean; see
  <xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-map-nb-article">Figure 1</xref>). His poetry is
  voluminous and varied, but the violence of the frontier, the ignorance
  of the settler, and the brutality of empire are key themes in many of
  his poems. He has been judged complicit in the imaginative
  expropriation of Aboriginal lands
  (<xref alt="Van Toorn 1992" rid="ref-van_toorn_terrors_1992-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Van
  Toorn 1992</xref>), and some of his poems do imagine Australia as a
  place of “solitude profound” before European settlement
  (<xref alt="Harpur 2019, h665a" rid="ref-harpur_charles_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  2019, h665a</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-nb-article">2</xref> In
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> (1843-1867), Harpur reckons with
  his own contradictory impulses. He acknowledges Indigenous Australians
  as the “former lords of the soil,” and includes 12 Indigenous words in
  the text of the poem. In a series of footnotes, he localises the words
  to particular Indigenous groups, and argues for the appropriateness of
  Indigenous words to poetry. The poem has a complex textual history—as
  do nearly all Harpur’s poems
  (<xref alt="Eggert 2016" rid="ref-eggert_charles_2016-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Eggert
  2016</xref>). The earliest evidence for the poem is an excerpt
  published in the <italic>Weekly Register</italic> in 1843
  (<xref alt="Harpur 1843" rid="ref-harpur_australian_1843-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  1843</xref>). At that time, Harpur was living at Jerrys Plains, in the
  upper Hunter Valley. All the surviving complete versions of the poem,
  however, date to the 1860s, when Harpur was living far to the south in
  Eurobodalla. Although Harpur revised the poem considerably,
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> retains is character as poem of the
  1840s, extolling the beauties of the “loud Nepean,” “old Hawkesbury”
  and “rapid Hunter” rivers where Harpur spent his youth and early
  adulthood (h209-bf). It is nonetheless tricky to precisely localise
  the poem’s Indigenous vocabulary.</p>
  <sec id="cell-fig-map-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
  <code language="r script"># Geoscience Australia topographic data
coastline &lt;- sf::read_sf(file.path(DATA_DIR, &quot;framework&quot;))</code>
  <code language="r script">rivers &lt;- sf::read_sf(file.path(DATA_DIR, &quot;drainage&quot;)) |&gt; 
  dplyr::filter(stringr::str_detect(NAME, &quot;HAWKESBURY|NEPEAN|HUNTER&quot;))

river_names &lt;- tibble::tribble(
  ~name, ~lon, ~lat,
  &quot;HUNTER RIVER&quot;, 151.35, -32.15,
  &quot;DEERUBBIN&quot;, 150.8, -33.3
)

# Based on Austlang and dictionaries
language_names &lt;- tibble::tribble(
  ~language, ~lon, ~lat, ~angle,
  &quot;Darkinyung&quot;, 150.82, -33.1, 0,
  &quot;Wiradjuri&quot;, 150, -33, 80,
  &quot;HRLM&quot;, 151.5, -32.75, 0,
  &quot;Gamilaraay&quot;, 150.4, -32.3, 0,
  &quot;Dharug&quot;, 150.9, -33.9, 0
)

# Geocoded from Nominatim
towns &lt;- readr::read_csv(file.path(DATA_DIR, &quot;towns.csv&quot;))</code>
  <code language="r script">ggplot2::ggplot() +
  ggplot2::geom_sf(data = coastline, colour=&quot;darkgrey&quot;) +
  ggplot2::geom_sf(data = rivers, colour=&quot;lightblue&quot;) +
  ggplot2::geom_point(data = towns, ggplot2::aes(x=longitude, y=latitude)) +
  ggplot2::geom_text(
    data = towns,
    ggplot2::aes(x=longitude, y=latitude, label=name),
    nudge_x=0.05, check_overlap = T, hjust=&quot;left&quot;, vjust=&quot;centre&quot;, family=&quot;mono&quot;
    ) +
  ggplot2::geom_text(
    data = river_names,
    ggplot2::aes(x=lon, y=lat, label=name),
    colour=&quot;darkgrey&quot;
  ) +
  ggplot2::geom_text(
    data=language_names,
    ggplot2::aes(x=lon, y=lat, label=language, angle=angle),
    fontface=&quot;bold&quot;,
    size=17,
    size.unit=&quot;pt&quot;,
    show.legend=F
  ) +
  ggplot2::coord_sf(xlim = c(149.9, 152.5), ylim = c(-32, -34)) +
  ggplot2::theme_classic() +
  ggspatial::annotation_scale(location=&quot;br&quot;) +
  ggplot2::labs(x=&quot;Longitude&quot;, y=&quot;Latitude&quot;)</code>
  <fig id="fig-map-nb-article">
    <caption><p>Figure 1: Deerubbin and the Hunter in the 1840s,
    indicating languages, settlements and rivers mentioned in the text.
    Sources: Geoscience Australia
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-geoscience_australia_geodata_2003-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>);
    Nominatim; Lissarrague
    (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>);
    Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon
    (<xref alt="2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>);
    Jones
    (<xref alt="2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>);
    Austlang.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="harpur-dunlop-wulatji_files/figure-jats/fig-map-1.png" />
  </fig>
  <sec id="cell-fig-map-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
  <preformat>Warning in CPL_read_ogr(dsn, layer, query, as.character(options), quiet, :
automatically selected the first layer in a data source containing more than
one.</preformat>
  </sec>
  <sec id="cell-fig-map-output-1-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
  <preformat>Rows: 7 Columns: 5
── Column specification ────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Delimiter: &quot;,&quot;
chr (3): name, address, query
dbl (2): latitude, longitude

ℹ Use `spec()` to retrieve the full column specification for this data.
ℹ Specify the column types or set `show_col_types = FALSE` to quiet this message.</preformat>
  </sec>
  </sec>
  <p>My comparison of Harpur and Dunlop has two aims. The first aim is
  to contrast Dunlop’s and Harpur’s poetics: I argue that Dunlop is a
  <italic>universalist</italic>, while Harpur is a
  <italic>particularist</italic>. The second aim is to clarify the
  problem of <italic>linguistic representation</italic>—or more
  verbosely, the <italic>literary representation of Indigenous
  languages</italic>.</p>
  <p>Both Dunlop and Harpur represent Indigenous language for
  humanitarian ends. Although Dunlop was highly sensitive to the
  differences between people, her “sentimental” poetics relies on the
  universality of human feelings to justify the universality of human
  rights
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021</xref>). Thus she attempts to demonstrate the universality of the
  poetic impulse by transcribing and translating a sample of Awabakal
  poetry. By contrast, Harpur attempts to do justice to Indigenous
  ecopoetics by drawing a link between the euphony of particular
  Indigenous words and the ecological knowledge of particular Indigenous
  people. Dunlop’s universalism and Harpur’s particularism have both
  been subject to scholarly critique, but have never been compared. I
  perform the comparison in sections
  <xref alt="2" rid="eliza-hamilton-dunlop-universalism-nb-article">2</xref> and
  <xref alt="3" rid="charles-harpur-particularism-nb-article">3</xref>.</p>
  <p>Dunlop and Harpur also raise the broader question of how to
  represent a language. Both Harpur and Dunlop wish to represent
  Indigenous languages as <italic>poetic</italic>, but they do so in
  different ways. Dunlop produces a <italic>transcription</italic>,
  <italic>translation</italic> and <italic>glossary</italic>; Harpur
  produces <italic>words</italic> and <italic>philological
  footnotes</italic> embedded in an original poem. These different forms
  of representation convey different ideas about the nature of
  Indigenous language. Dunlop presents Wulatji’s language (the Hunter
  River Lake Macquarie language, or HRLM), as <italic>syntactic</italic>
  and <italic>literary.</italic> Harpur presents the various languages
  of his poem, namely Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and HRLM, as
  <italic>verbal</italic> and <italic>oral</italic>. Despite these
  differences, Dunlop and Harpur draw on a similar stock of ideas about
  human language, rooted in the empiricist linguistics that then reigned
  in the English-speaking world. I demonstrate this shared background in
  <xref alt="section 4" rid="linguistic-representation-and-the-conquest-of-space-nb-article">section
  4</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="eliza-hamilton-dunlop-universalism-nb-article">
  <title>2 Eliza Hamilton Dunlop: Universalism</title>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Since morning stars first sang in prayerful praise,
    Since Adam’s hymns resounded over space,
    Or Sinai’s hill trembled in glory’s blaze;
    Immortal song hath had acknowledged place.
    (<xref alt="Dunlop 1872b, ll. 1–4" rid="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    1872b, ll. 1–4</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>For Dunlop, “song” is a universal feature of human nature. In the
  opening lines of “Poesy,” she hears song in three places: in nature
  (the “morning stars”), in oral tradition (“Adam’s hymns”), and in
  written literature (“On Sinai’s hill,” where Moses receives the tables
  of the law). In all these places, the same force of “song” is heard.
  At all <italic>times</italic>, too, this “song” is heard, for it is
  “Immortal.” Song is immortal and ubiquitous, Dunlop continues, because
  it is an “Essence inherent of the sentient mind”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop 1872b, l. 5" rid="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  1872b, l. 5</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-nb-article">3</xref> Always and
  everywhere, humans are poets.</p>
  <p>Dunlop’s belief in the universality of song had deep ethical and
  intellectual roots. She was a “sentimentalist,” whose poetry teaches
  that “the emotional experiences of others are similar to our own”
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021, 91" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021, 91</xref>). She was an “internationalist,” whose poetry
  describes the struggle for freedom among all the oppressed peoples of
  the British Empire
  (<xref alt="Wu 2021, 60" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wu
  2021, 60</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston and Webby 2021, 9" rid="ref-johnston_proud_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  and Webby 2021, 9</xref>). She was a polyglot, whose poems speak in
  many tongues
  (<xref alt="Wafer 2021, 158–59" rid="ref-wafer_unmapping_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wafer
  2021, 158–59</xref>). Thus she expressed her humanitarian ideals in
  the rhetoric, content and vocabulary of her poetry.</p>
  <p>As Rudy
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)
  insists, Dunlop’s universalism was not naive. She grew up in Ireland
  in the wake of the United Irish uprising and the abolition of the
  Irish parliament. She visited India, where she befriended her
  “half-caste” sisters.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-nb-article">4</xref> She
  settled in Australia, where she displayed an exceptional facility for
  Indigenous languages, particularly their phonetics
  (<xref alt="Johnston 2021, 46" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 46</xref>), and where she campaigned publicly for the rights of
  Indigenous Australians. In all these places, she was sensitive to
  local conditions. She published some 100 poems in Irish and Australian
  newspapers; when she did so, she chose her words carefully for local
  readers, especially when republishing Irish works in Australia
  (<xref alt="Rudy 2021, 94" rid="ref-rudy_beyond_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Rudy
  2021, 94</xref>). Her universalism was modulated by her pragmatic
  sense of audience.</p>
  <p>It is in this context that we should understand her transcription
  and translation of Wulatji’s poetry. The transcription is short enough
  to quote in full. Its language is Awabakal, recognised today as a
  variety of the Hunter River Lake Macquarie language (HRLM):</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba wonung bulkirra umbilinto bulwarra;
    Pital burra kultan wirripang bunto
    Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba turrama berrambo, burra kilkoa:
    Kurri wi, raratoa yella walliko,
    Yulo Moane, woinya, birung poro bulliko[.]
    Nung-Ngnun
    Nge a runba kan wullung, Makora, kokein,
    Mip-pa-rai, kekul, wimbi murr ring kirrika:
    Nge a runba mura ke-en kulbun kulbun murrung.
    (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
    1848</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>It is difficult to say what precisely this is a transcription
  <italic>of</italic>. O’Leary
  (<xref alt="2004, 92" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2004,
  92</xref>) argues from manuscript evidence that Dunlop fashioned a
  single poem from “three short songs” by Wulatji. In a manuscript she
  prepared in the 1870s, she does indeed label the three sections “Song
  1,” “Song 2” and “Song 3”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop, n.d." rid="ref-dunlop_vase_nodate-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop,
  n.d.</xref>, image 60; printed in
  <xref alt="Dunlop 2021, 194" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  2021, 194</xref>). In both the published version and the manuscript,
  she gives each section the heading “Nung-Ngung”
  (<italic>nannguyn</italic>, “song”). Despite this evidence, Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
  argues that Wulatji’s poetry should actually be seen as four “verses”
  of two lines each. He gives two arguments: the four-verse
  interpretation makes the poetry more metrically consistent
  (<xref alt="2017, 204" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  204</xref>); and the textual evidence cannot be trusted, because there
  is no record of Dunlop and Wulatji’s conversations
  (<xref alt="2017, 202" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  202</xref>). Did Wulatji produce one or more discrete texts at
  Dunlop’s request, knowing they might be published? Did he perform at a
  ceremony or gathering that Dunlop observed? Did he produce a series of
  verse-examples to try and teach her about Awabakal versification? Did
  he improvise a performance to impress
  her?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-nb-article">5</xref> Dunlop herself provides
  evidence that it may be foolish to precisely number the poems in
  Wulatji’s text. In the manuscript version of the poem, she notes that
  Indigenous songs are short and “often repeated in a variety of
  cadence”
  (<xref alt="2021, 194" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2021,
  194</xref>). How many different verses would a poet like Wulatji
  “repeat” in a single performance? It is not necessarily the case that
  his poetry could be neatly divided into discrete “poems” independent
  of one another.</p>
  <p>Dunlop preserves this ambiguity in her transcription and
  translation. Her title, “Native Poetry,” does not specify the number
  of poems. When she adapted her translation into an original song for
  Isaac Nathan, she used a similarly indeterminate title, “Pialla
  Wollombi,” which she glosses as “the poetry or language of Wollombi”
  (<xref alt="Dunlop and Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
  and Wulatji 1848</xref>). All this is to suggest that Dunlop does not
  transcribe a <italic>text</italic>, but rather a
  <italic>corpus</italic> of Awabakal verse. She provides the reader a
  sample of Wulatji’s poetry, and shapes it into a single translation
  for readerly consumption—for the <italic>translation</italic>, unlike
  the transcription, certainly comprises a single text:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Our home is the gibber-gunyah,
    Where hill joins hill on high;
    Where the turruma and berrambo,
    Like sleeping serpents lie;
    And the rushing of wings, as the wangas pass,
    Sweeps the wallaby’s print from the glistening grass.
    Ours are the makoro gliding,
    Deep in the shady pool;
    For our spear is sure, and the prey secure…
    Kanin, or the bright gherool.
    Our lubras sleep by the bato clear,
    That the Amygest’s track hath never been near.
    Ours is the koolema flowing
    With precious kirrika stored;
    For fleet the foot, and keen the eye,
    That seeks the nukkung’s hoard;
    And the glances are bright, and the footsteps are free,
    When we dance in the shade of the karakon tree.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>There are many remarkable features of this translation, but for our
  purposes, the most important aspect is its vocabulary
  (<xref alt="Table 1" rid="tbl-dunlop-lang-nb-article">Table 1</xref>). Dunlop
  includes 15 Indigenous words in her translation. Five of these had
  already been incorporated into Australian English by 1848:
  “gibber-gunyah,” “wallaby,” “wanga,” “lubra”, and probably “koolema”
  (<xref alt="Dixon et al. 2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dixon
  et al. 2006</xref>). She nonetheless includes two of
  them—“gibber-gunyah” and “wanga”—in the poem’s Glossary. The other 10
  words probably appear here in English verse for the first time, and
  probably all originate in Wulatji’s speech (“gherool” and “Amygest”
  being the difficult cases).</p>
  <sec id="nb-code-cell-2-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
  <code language="r script">knitr::kable(dunlop)</code>
  <fig id="tbl-dunlop-lang-nb-article">
    <caption><p>Table 1: Indigenous vocabulary in Dunlop’s translation
    of Wulatji. Sources: Wafer
    (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>);
    HRLM
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague 2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague
    2006</xref>); Darkinyung
    (<xref alt="Jones 2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Jones
    2008</xref>); Gamilaraay
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
    Ash, and Giacon 2003</xref>); Sydney
    (<xref alt="Troy 1993" rid="ref-troy_sydney_1993-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Troy
    1993</xref>); Dixon et al.
    (<xref alt="2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</p></caption>
    <table-wrap>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="10%" />
          <col width="7%" />
          <col width="9%" />
          <col width="33%" />
          <col width="41%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Dunlop’s translation</th>
            <th align="left">Wulatji’s text</th>
            <th align="left">Dunlop’s definition</th>
            <th align="left">HRLM equivalents</th>
            <th align="left">Other equivalents</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gibber-gunyah</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Cave in the rock</td>
            <td align="left">kuyung ~ kuyang <italic>camp, camp fire;
            also town</italic></td>
            <td align="left">giba <italic>stone or rock</italic>, gunya
            <italic>hut</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">turruma</td>
            <td align="left">turrama</td>
            <td align="left">War arms</td>
            <td align="left">TaRama <italic>war boomerang</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">berrambo</td>
            <td align="left">berrambo</td>
            <td align="left">War arms</td>
            <td align="left">pirampu <italic>waddy; club
            (Wafer)</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wanga</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">A species of pigeon</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wungawunga <italic>Wonga pigeon</italic>
            (Sydney); wangawanga <italic>Wonga pigeon</italic>
            (Darkinyung)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wallaby</td>
            <td align="left">buntoa</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">walapi ~ walapay <italic>wallaby</italic>;
            paNTarr <italic>kangaroo</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wulaba <italic>rock wallaby</italic>
            (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">makoro</td>
            <td align="left">Makoro</td>
            <td align="left">Fish</td>
            <td align="left">makurr <italic>fish</italic></td>
            <td align="left">magura <italic>fish</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kanim</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Eel</td>
            <td align="left">kaNiyn ~ KaNang <italic>freshwater
            eel</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gherool</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Mullet</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">djirul <italic>mullet</italic>
            (Darkinyung)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">lubra</td>
            <td align="left">mura ke-en</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">marr[a]kiyn <italic>young maiden, woman,
            girl</italic></td>
            <td align="left">[The etymology of <italic>lubra</italic> is
            unknown; possibly from a Tasmanian language] (Dixon et
            al)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">bato</td>
            <td align="left">kokein</td>
            <td align="left">Water</td>
            <td align="left">paTu, kukuyn <italic>fresh
            water</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Amygest</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">White fellow</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">koolema</td>
            <td align="left">wimbi</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wimpi <italic>vessel made from the knots of
            trees and used as baskets or bowls</italic></td>
            <td align="left">guliman <italic>coolamon</italic>
            (Gamilaraay)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kirrika</td>
            <td align="left">kirrika</td>
            <td align="left">Honey</td>
            <td align="left">kiR[i]ka <italic>white honey</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">nukkung</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Wild bee</td>
            <td align="left">Nakang <italic>native bee</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">karakun</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">Oak Tree</td>
            <td align="left">karakaNpa <italic>place of
            swamp-oaks</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </fig>
  </sec>
  <p>What is remarkable is the relationship between Dunlop’s words and
  Wulatji’s. We might expect Dunlop only to introduce Indigenous words
  in her poem if they are present in Wulatji’s text, or common in
  Australian English. But this is not her practice. In just four cases,
  Dunlop incorporates a word from Wulatji’s text into her translation:
  “turruma”, “berrambo”, “makoro” and “kirrika.” In the other cases, she
  either inserts a new word into the poem (e.g. “wanga,” “nukkung”) or
  translates one of Wulatji’s words by a <italic>different</italic>
  Indigenous word (e.g. “kokein” → “bato”, “wimbi” → “koolema”). Her
  translation ultimately incorporates vocabulary from at least three or
  four Australian languages, but in neither the text nor the Glossary
  does she indicate which languages they are. Dunlop effectively
  develops her own poetic language, combining English, Wulatji’s own
  speech, and the speech of other Indigenous peoples across Eastern NSW.
  She confers unity on Wulatji’s verses, combining them into a single
  poem, and she confers unity on the languages of the colony, combining
  them into a single tongue. How should we interpret this unity?</p>
  <p>Dunlop’s translation is a representation of Indigenous speech. Thus
  it has two interlinked aims: it must capture the lyrical qualities of
  Wulatji’s verse; and it must signal its Indigenous Australian origin
  to the reader. In this light, the inclusion of familiar words such as
  “gibber-gunyah” and “wallaby” makes sense. These words signal to the
  reader that this is an “Australian” poem. The choice to translate
  Wulatji’s words by other words sometimes serves this purpose of
  familiarisation (e.g. “mura ke-en” → “lubra”), and sometimes seems to
  be an aesthetic decision: e.g. Dunlop presumably found “bato clear”
  more euphonious than “kokein clear” or alternative phrasings. The
  poem’s rhyme and metre also serve these dual purposes of
  familiarisation and exoticism. The rhymes follow the familiar
  <italic>ababcc</italic> scheme of Shakespeare’s <italic>Venus and
  Adonis</italic> (1593). Meanwhile the accentual metre emulates the old
  ballads that represented “tradition” for Romantic readers. The number
  of beats follows a fixed pattern in each stanza (3-3-4-3-4-4), while
  the rhythm shifts freely between binary and ternary. In sum, Dunlop
  presents Wulatji’s poetry as though it is an ancient ballad in an
  “invented tradition” of Australian verse, the kind of poem you might
  encounter in Thomas Percy’s <italic>Reliques of Ancient English
  Poetry</italic> (1765) or Walter Scott’s <italic>Minstrelsy of the
  Scottish Border</italic> (1802).</p>
  <p>To turn Wulatji’s poem into a “Relique” of Australian verse, Dunlop
  amplifies the text. Wulatji’s original text is not remotely
  ballad-like. It has a terseness that bespeaks its rich metaphysical
  background. Wafer
  (<xref alt="2017, 206" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  206</xref>) translates the first verse thus:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Ours is the place where the mountains cohabit with the heights
    The eaglehawks and wallabies are happy</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>When she chooses, Dunlop captures the literal sense of Wulatji’s
  verse well, e.g. “wonung bulkirra umbilinto bulwarra” → “where hill
  joins hill on high.” But she generally amplifies the verse to conform
  with European expectations of the lyric. Human embodiment is implicit
  in Wulatji’s poem. Dunlop makes it explicit, indicating that the
  mountains are Wulatji’s “home.” The senses are muted in Wulatji’s
  poem. Dunlop invokes the senses, so that the birds have “rushing
  wings,” and the wallabies play on the “glistening grass.” She also,
  inexplicably, turns Wulatji’s “wirripang” (“eaglehawk”) into a Wonga
  pigeon. These amplifications are typical of Dunlop’s translation. She
  inserts individual persons into the poem, placing their bodies in the
  landscape and invoking their sensory experiences of nature.</p>
  <p>Dunlop thus presents Wulatji’s verse as <italic>syntactic</italic>
  and <italic>literary</italic>. It is not the individual words of his
  poetry that matter, but their connection into smoothly-flowing verse.
  And though Wulatji’s verse is oral rather than written, Dunlop
  presents it as implictly literary, like the ancient “Reliques” of
  English verse preserved in book and manuscript. Dunlop emphasises the
  syntax and literacy of Wulatji’s verse in her introduction to the
  poem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>There is a god of Poesy, Wallatu, who composes music, and who,
    without temple, shrine, or statue, is as universally acknowledged as
    if his oracles were breathed by Belus or Osiris: he comes in dreams,
    and transports the individual to some sunny hill, where he is
    inspired with the supernatural gift.
    (<xref alt="Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-wulatji_native_1848-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wulatji
    1848</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Wulatji’s poetry is syntactic because it does not comprise
  individual words. Instead it comes complete, in the form of “oracles”
  delivered by divine inspiration. Wulatji’s poetry is literary because
  the god of his inspiration, Wallatu, is the same in kind as the gods
  of the Celts (Belus) and Egyptians (Osiris), whose writings lie at the
  origins of Western civilisation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-nb-article">6</xref>
  Dunlop the Irish writer recognises in Wulatji a fellow Celt. And this
  is unsurprising, because “Poesy” is universal, and can be recognised
  as easily in Australia as anywhere else. Thus the freedom of Dunlop’s
  translation. She does not translate the literal sense of the words,
  but communicates the “Poesy” that inspires them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="charles-harpur-particularism-nb-article">
  <title>3 Charles Harpur: Particularism</title>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>A thousand bright particulars are given,
    And they outshine the very stars of heaven! (“Ideality”, h185b)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Harpur’s poem is on a grander scale than Dunlop’s. <italic>The
  Kangaroo Hunt, or A Morning in the Mountains: A Descriptive Poem in
  Six Parts: By Charles Harpur. An Australian</italic> is a long and
  ambitious work that has been described as “Australia’s first epic
  poem”
  (<xref alt="Gelder and Weaver 2020, 81" rid="ref-gelder_colonial_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Gelder
  and Weaver 2020, 81</xref>). It describes an “idealised” kangaroo hunt
  that lasts from sunrise to sunset. As the youthful party of white
  hunters harry the kangaroo, Harpur describes the sights and sounds of
  the Australian bush, expanding on the verse in detailed footnotes. The
  poem pulls in two directions. In one direction, Harpur seeks to
  “idealise” the hunt, blending the details of many possible hunts into
  “one Eden-piece embathed with a luminous atmosphere of sentiment”
  (h209-af). In another direction, Harpur seeks to capture specific
  details of land and language, to capture the particular qualities of
  each bird, tree, geological feature—or Indigenous word. We will see
  that in his hunt for particularity, Harpur presents Indigenous
  languages as primarily <italic>oral</italic> and
  <italic>verbal</italic>. A language comprises words that are spoken by
  particular people in particular places.</p>
  <p>Harpur uses 12 Indigenous words in either the body of the poem or
  its footnotes
  (<xref alt="Table 2" rid="tbl-harpur-lang-nb-article">Table 2</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-nb-article">7</xref>
  Generally speaking, Harpur’s transcriptions are sound, and it is not
  difficult to look up the words in a modern dictionary. It is
  nonetheless difficult to identify the languages of Harpur’s poem, for
  two main reasons. The first reason is lack of biographical evidence.
  Harpur does not name his informants, nor does he describe precisely
  where he encountered them. The only geographic detail he provides is
  in his footnote on the words “jimbuc” and “whirring”, which I discuss
  below. The second reason lies in the textual record. Harpur began the
  poem in the 1840s, while living on the Hunter, and completed it in the
  1860s, while living in Eurobodalla. With the exception of a single
  extract published in the <italic>Weekly Register</italic> in 1843, all
  the surviving versions of the poem date to the 1860s
  (<xref alt="Harpur 1843" rid="ref-harpur_australian_1843-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Harpur
  1843</xref>). Only <italic>one</italic> Indigenous word, “duaralli,”
  appears in the 1843 newspaper extract. When did Harpur learn and
  insert the other words? Despite these problems, it is possible to find
  all but one of Harpur’s words in modern dictionaries.</p>
  <sec id="nb-code-cell-3-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
  <code language="r script">knitr::kable(harpur)</code>
  <fig id="tbl-harpur-lang-nb-article">
    <caption><p>Table 2: Indigenous Vocabulary in <italic>The Kangaroo
    Hunt</italic>. Sources: Darkinyung
    (<xref alt="Jones 2008" rid="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Jones
    2008</xref>); HRLM
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague 2006" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague
    2006</xref>); Gamilaraay
    (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
    Ash, and Giacon 2003</xref>); Wiradjuri
    (<xref alt="Grant, Grant, and Rudder 2010" rid="ref-grant_new_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Grant,
    Grant, and Rudder 2010</xref>); Dhurga
    (<xref alt="Ellis et al. 2020" rid="ref-ellis_dhurga_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ellis
    et al. 2020</xref>); Sydney
    (<xref alt="Troy 1993" rid="ref-troy_sydney_1993-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Troy
    1993</xref>); also Jim Wafer, personal communication.</p></caption>
    <table-wrap>
      <table>
        <colgroup>
          <col width="5%" />
          <col width="41%" />
          <col width="9%" />
          <col width="10%" />
          <col width="14%" />
          <col width="7%" />
          <col width="15%" />
        </colgroup>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Harpur’s word</th>
            <th align="left">Harpur’s definition</th>
            <th align="left">Referent</th>
            <th align="left">Darkinyung</th>
            <th align="left">HRLM</th>
            <th align="left">Gamilaraay</th>
            <th align="left">Other</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Euroka</td>
            <td align="left">“an aboriginal name of the sun”</td>
            <td align="left">the sun</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">panyal</td>
            <td align="left">yaraay</td>
            <td align="left">yurraga (Wiradjuri); yuraga (Dhurga)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">bidawong</td>
            <td align="left">“flying squirrel”</td>
            <td align="left">glider</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">pitjang</td>
            <td align="left">bagu</td>
            <td align="left">budha-rang (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">kindyne</td>
            <td align="left">“ring-tailed possum”</td>
            <td align="left">ring-tailed possum</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>gindang</bold></td>
            <td align="left">wilay <italic>possum</italic></td>
            <td align="left">garrawir</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">gooburra</td>
            <td align="left">“the large kind of king-fisher which is
            commonly known by the tasteful and poetic sobriquet of the
            Laughing Jackass”</td>
            <td align="left">kookaburra</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>kukaparr</bold></td>
            <td align="left">gugurrgaagaa</td>
            <td align="left">gugubarra (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">teleltella</td>
            <td align="left">“a large and solitary kind of
            bell-bird”</td>
            <td align="left">crested bellbird</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">banbandhuluwi</td>
            <td align="left">dilbanyi <italic>ring–to ring as a
            bell</italic> (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">warragl</td>
            <td align="left">“an aboriginal name of the native dog”</td>
            <td align="left">wild dog</td>
            <td align="left">miri <italic>dog, wild dog</italic></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>waRikal</bold></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wuragal (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">yerowala</td>
            <td align="left">“blue-mountain parrot”</td>
            <td align="left">rainbow lorikeet</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>wagarala</bold>
            <italic>parrot</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wakalarr ~ wakilarr <italic>red parrot;
            rosella</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">wiragala <italic>australian
            ringneck</italic> (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">duaralli</td>
            <td align="left">“the kangaroo-rat;” attributed to “the
            blacks of the Hunter” in 1843, but to “blacks of the
            interior” in 1867 (h209-df)</td>
            <td align="left">eastern bettong</td>
            <td align="left">dhurawayi</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>dhurrawaay</bold></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">maroo</td>
            <td align="left">“a sort of brush iron-wood”</td>
            <td align="left">?grey box</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>maru</bold> <italic>thorny
            bush</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">wallaroo</td>
            <td align="left">“wallaroo”; “the male … [is] almost black,
            and the female … [is] a sort of cream color”</td>
            <td align="left">eastern wallaroo</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>walaru</bold> <italic>black
            kangaroo</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left">yulama</td>
            <td align="left">wularu (Sydney)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">jimbuc</td>
            <td align="left">“a little shag-haired species of kangaroo;”
            metaphorically, “sheep”</td>
            <td align="left">brush-tailed rock wallaby</td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
            <td align="left"><bold>dhimba</bold>
            <italic>sheep</italic></td>
            <td align="left"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">whirring</td>
            <td align="left">name for “jimbuck” among the people of “the
            Hawksbury mountains”</td>
            <td align="left">brush-tailed rock wallaby</td>
            <td align="left"><bold>wirayn</bold></td>
            <td align="left">wayiring <italic>wallaby</italic></td>
            <td align="left">wan.guy</td>
            <td align="left">wirrang (Wiradjuri)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </fig>
  </sec>
  <p>The linguistic evidence suggests that the language of the poem is
  primarily Darkinyung, HRLM and Gamilaraay. This finding is consistent
  with the one biographical clue that Harpur provides in the poem. The
  clue lies in the word “jimbuc,” which Harpur attributes to the “Blacks
  of the Hunter,” as opposed to the “blacks of the Hawksbury
  mountains:”</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Jimbuc is an aboriginal name of little shag-haired species of
    kangaroo which is peculiar to mountain copses. It may be called the
    mountain wallaby, being in relation to the wallaroo what the common
    wallaby is to the kangaroo proper. The jimbuc is the least elegant
    in its form, and the dullest in its nature, of all the kangaroo
    kinds—of all such at least as I happen to be acquainted with. The
    Blacks of the Hunter call the sheep jimbuc, no doubt from a
    resemblance, however remote, arising out of the hairy shagginess of
    the one and the woolliness of the other. But this, like most other
    of our indigenous animals, is named variously by the aboriginal
    tribes of different localities: and is (or was) known amongst the
    Hawksbury mountains by the native name of <italic>whirring</italic>.
    (h209-gf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>By the “Hawksbury mountains,” Harpur presumably refers to the rocky
  highlands that lie between Deebrubbin and the Hunter Valley. If this
  is so, then the language he would most likely encounter in that region
  is Darkinyung. The first road between Sydney and the Hunter Valley ran
  through this region Harpur calls the “Hawksbury mountains,” so Harpur
  is likely to have traversed the region numerous times when moving
  between the Hunter, Deerubbin and Sydney.</p>
  <p>The case for “the Blacks of the Hunter” is more difficult. In the
  1840s and 50s, Harpur spent most of his time moving around Singleton
  and Jerrys Plains. According to Lissarrague
  (<xref alt="2006, 13" rid="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2006,
  13</xref>), this was a bilingual zone. Towards the east, the Wonnarua
  and Geawagal spoke varieties of HRLM, Wulatji’s tongue. Towards the
  west, the people spoke another language, and the available sources are
  unclear what it was. Lissarrague suspects it was either Gamilaraay or
  Darkinyung. Since Darkinyung is the most likely candidate for Harpur’s
  language of the “Hawksbury mountains,” his language of the “Hunter” is
  more likely to be Gamilaraay. This is broadly consistent with
  <xref alt="Table 2" rid="tbl-harpur-lang-nb-article">Table 2</xref>, which shows
  that there is a compelling Darkinyung, HRLM, or Gamilaraay equivalent
  for nine of Harpur’s 12 Indigenous words (marked in bold).</p>
  <p>The example of “jimbuc” supports this general picture. Today,
  <italic>jumbuck</italic> is cherished by settler Australians as a
  slang word for sheep, immortalised in the popular song
  <italic>Waltzing Matilda</italic>. Dixon et al.
  (<xref alt="2006, 56" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2006,
  56</xref>) suggest that the word may derive from English
  <italic>jump</italic>, or perhaps from the Gamilaraay word
  <italic>dhimba</italic>, but admit that neither hypothesis can be
  “confirmed.” Harpur’s footnote provides concerete support for the
  hypothesis that <italic>jumbuck</italic> derives from Gamilaraay
  <italic>dhimba</italic>. The hypothesis gains strength given the
  specificity of Harpur’s description: Harpur insists that the word
  referred specifically to the “mountain wallaby,” which from his
  description is clearly the brush-tailed rock wallaby
  (<italic>Petrogale penicillata</italic>). The compilers of the modern
  <italic>Gamilaraay-Yuwalaraay-Yuwaalayaay</italic> dictionary were
  unable to find a word specifically for the brush-tailed-rock wallaby,
  and record the word <italic>dhimba</italic> solely in its meaning of
  <italic>sheep</italic>
  (<xref alt="Lissarrague, Ash, and Giacon 2003, 62" rid="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Lissarrague,
  Ash, and Giacon 2003, 62</xref>). If we can trust Harpur’s testimony
  on this point, then the old riddle of <italic>jumbuck</italic> is
  solved, and we can be surer that some of Harpur’s informants in the
  Hunter spoke Gamilaraay.</p>
  <p>Although it seems certain that Harpur learned most of the words
  directly from Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and HRLM speakers, some of the
  words present problems. It is of course quite probable that Harpur
  learned the words “wallaroo,” “gooburra” and “warragl” simply by
  learning English: these words had passed into Australian English from
  Wiradjuri and the Sydney language by the 1830s
  (<xref alt="Dixon et al. 2006" rid="ref-dixon_australian_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dixon
  et al. 2006</xref>). The real problem words are “Euroka,” “bidawong”
  and “teleltella.”</p>
  <p>The origin of “teleltella” is most obscure. Wafer (personal
  communication) suggests that <italic>dilbanyi</italic>, a word in the
  Sydney Language, could be a possible source. Gamilaraay
  <italic>banbandhuluwi</italic> has a promising number of syllables and
  the correct meaning, but the vowels and consonants differ considerably
  from Harpur’s transcription. It is possible that “teleltella”
  represents a hitherto unattested Darkinyung or HRLM word: no word for
  “crested bellbird” appears in either dictionary.</p>
  <p>The other problem words, “bidawong” and “Euroka,” are attested in
  Wiradjuri, a language spoken in regions bordering Darkinyung, HRLM and
  Gamilaraay. “Euroka” is also attested in Dhurga, the local language of
  the south coast where Harpur was living in the 1860s. The data suggest
  three hypotheses: (1) Harpur had Wiradjuri informants; (2) “bidawong”
  and/or “Euroka” were present in Darkinyung but are hitherto
  unattested; (3) Harpur inserted the word “Euroka” into the poem after
  he learned it from Dhurga speakers in the 1860s. If hypothesis (1) is
  true, it would suggest that the area west of Singleton may have been
  trilingual, with speakers of Wiradjuri, HRLM and Gamilaraay all
  frequently present. If hypotheses (2) and/or (3) are true, this would
  be consistent with Lissarrague’s surmise that the area west of
  Singleton was a transitional zone between HRLM and Gamilaraay. These
  hypotheses are hard to adjudicate, given the lack of corroborating
  evidence, but all are consistent with the general impression that
  Harpur learned most of his Indigenous vocabulary directly from local
  Indigenous informants in the 1830s and 40s.</p>
  <p>While the <italic>facts</italic> of the case are murky, the
  <italic>poetics</italic> are clear. In sharp distinction to Dunlop,
  Harpur presents each word as a particular word spoken by particular
  people in a particular place. “Jimbuc” and “whirring” are only the
  most obvious instances. Consider these lines from Part II, when Harpur
  describes the sunrise:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Uncovered no longer the forest dog prowls,
    Though so bold in the dark;
    And the kindynef and bidawongg haste to their holes
    In the spouts of yon old ironbark:
    While on its one bare blasted limb
    The gooburrah sits in the fog-wreath dim,
    Glorying loud with a laughter-like glee
    In the march of the dayspring’s victory […] (h209-cf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In each footnote, Harpur identifies the word as “an Aboriginal
  name”, emphasising the indefinite article in footnote
  <italic>g</italic>: “I say <italic>an</italic> aboriginal name,
  because almost every tribe of Blacks has a different set of names for
  our indiginous animals.” (h209-cf) His precision about language is
  linked to his precision about nature. He places each animal in its
  ecological niche: the dog’s hunting patterns change in the daytime,
  the “bidawong” (glider) and “kindyne” (ring-tailed possum) nest
  specifically in the “ironbark,” and the kookaburra sits on a “bare”
  branch where it can see its prey. Dixon
  (<xref alt="1980, 322" rid="ref-dixon_charles_1980-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1980,
  322</xref>) compares the poem to a “natural history painting,” which
  presents a “typical and comprehensive cross section of the forest
  environment.” Natural history provides a ground-truth for Harpur’s
  analysis of names. Each animal or plant can be classified by species,
  then an appropriate name for the species can be selected from colonial
  English or local Indigenous languages. In one case, Harpur invents his
  <italic>own</italic> word for a species, having failed to locate an
  appropriate name. His invented name for the eastern whip-bird, “Jehu,”
  alludes to the bird’s colonial nickname of “coachman’s whip” (h209-gf,
  note d).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-nb-article">8</xref></p>
  <p>Harpur chooses Indigenous names because they are more “poetic.” For
  instance, to justify the choice of “gooburra” as a name for the
  kookaburra, he sarcastically dismisses the “the tasteful and poetic
  sobriquet of the Laughing Jackass” conferred on the bird by white
  settlers (h209-cf). His discussion of Indigenous names is most
  pregnant in the case of “Euroka,” which he invokes in Part I of the
  poem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Or while Eurokab first displays
    His burning rim on the ancient hill,
    […]
    He floods abroad his golden light
    In one unbroken mass immense
    Of life-essential influence […]
    b Euroka is an aboriginal name of the sun. It is at once euphonious
    and robust, and has therefore a certain sounding adequacy as a
    vocable, and thence somewhat of ideal unison with the golden
    progression and godlike port of that paramount luminary.
    (h209-bf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Harpur makes two claims for “Euroka.” First, the word itself is
  “euphonious and robust” as a “vocable.” Second, the word’s euphony
  means it can achieve an “ideal unison” with the reality it
  denotes—namely, the sun. For Harpur, the “ideality” of poetry arises
  from the unification of word and
  world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-nb-article">9</xref> To idealise the world,
  the poet must see each particular thing correctly, and then the select
  the word that will communicate that particularity. Harpur thus makes a
  strong claim for Indigenous poetics. Twelve times in <italic>The
  Kangaroo Hunt</italic>, Harpur claims that Indigenous people have
  properly seen the world, and found the ideal word to communicate what
  they have seen
  (<xref alt="Webby 2013, 5" rid="ref-webby_representations_2013-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Webby
  2013, 5</xref>). In the case of Euroka, Harpur emphasises the point by
  using Euroka himself as a symbol of ideality. Euroka illuminates the
  earth, uniting all things in the “one unbroken mass” of his
  “life-essential influence.”</p>
  <p>Harpur observes Euroka rise, but does not actually invoke him as
  the muse. Instead, Harpur compares himself to Euroka: as Euroka rises
  to illuminate the world, so the poet walks to the top of a hill to
  survey the scene. At this point in the poem, its troubling colonial
  elements come into view:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>While thus Euroka riseth red,
    Up, even to the kingly head
    Of some proud eminence, we climb,
    Where high amid the crags sublime,
    Australia’s yet unchristened Muse,
    A wandering Spirit of beauty rare,
    Loves oft to gem her streaming hair
    With heaven’s selectest dews,
    And scarf her bosom bright and bare
    With a robe of Morning richest hues;
    Giving the while to all objects there,
    All sounds,—the water drip just heard—
    The hum of insect—voice of bird,—
    To every echo and every air
    A poetry unfelt elsewhere. (h209-bf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In this image, Harpur illuminates the world with the ideal beauty
  of poetry, just as Euroka illuminates the world with his light. But
  the introduction of “Australia’s yet unchristened Muse” complicates
  things. What does “unchristened” mean? Does it mean that the Muse is
  unnamed, or simply that she has not “yet” been named by the Christian
  settlers? In either case, what is the significance of her naming?
  Harpur defends Indigenous speech as “euphonious” and “poetic.” He
  suggests that the poetry of the forest can be seen in the “dew,” heard
  in “All sounds,” and “felt” in the air. He suggests that the Muse is
  solar-powered, as Euroka “robes” her in beauty. Harpur himself
  refrains from naming the Muse in this very poem where he foreshadows
  her “christening.” Does all this mean that the Muse of Australia is
  eternal, and freely available to any human being to happens to walk in
  her domain? Or, more darkly, does Harpur propose that the white
  settlers will one day expropriate the Muse from the first Australians,
  by “christening” her? Harpur does not resolve these issues.
  <italic>The Kangaroo Hunt</italic> is a poem of futurity, and Harpur
  looks forward to a time when the poem’s own questions may be
  answered.</p>
  <p>In the final lines of the poem, however, Harpur does recur to the
  Muse. In these lines, Harpur describes himself as an “uncouth” poet,
  and apologises for his lack of education. He then aligns his own
  “uncouthness” with the “virginity” of the Muse:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Thus nurtured,—self urged, first he knew
    Australia’s virgin Muse to woo,
    And of Song’s bright mysteries ’gan to guess
    With a lone self-cherished studiousness […] (h209-gf)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Again the imagery is ambiguous. Does the virginity of the Muse
  imply that one day, she will marry the white settlers? Or does it
  imply that she is <italic>always</italic> a virgin, and that the
  poetry of Australia truly belongs to no-one, neither settler nor
  Indigenous? Harpur forecloses a third possibility, that the Muse was
  already married when the white settlers came. He is anxious to secure
  his poetic authority. Without the benefit of education, he claims
  authority from his connection to the land. But he realises full well
  that Indigenous Australians already have this connection. In Part III,
  Harpur acknowledges Indigenous Australians as “the former lords of the
  soil.” He praises their wise husbandry, which prevented the mass
  “extinction” of native birds brought about by white settlement
  (h209-df, note e). The wise husbandry and poetic speech of Indigenous
  Australians are both a problem and a solution for Harpur. Indigenous
  Australians have proven there is an Australian poetry inherent in the
  land, but they also threaten the white settler’s right to compose that
  poetry. The unnamed, unmarried “Muse of Australia” is Harpur’s attempt
  to resolve this contradiction.</p>
  <p>Where Dunlop’s translation is smooth and familiar, Harpur’s epic is
  craggy and difficult. He enjoins the reader to pause on each word,
  each image, and appreciate its robustness. Thus in the poem’s
  <italic>language</italic> as well as its plot, Harpur dramatises the
  struggle to comprehend the Australian environment. This struggle
  reflects broader themes in Harpur’s work: his struggle to cement his
  authority as the colony’s “first” poet
  (<xref alt="Mead 1990" rid="ref-mead_charles_1990-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Mead
  1990</xref>); and his interest in the struggle between “nature and
  intellect” in cognition
  (<xref alt="Ackland 1983, 460" rid="ref-ackland_charles_1983-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ackland
  1983, 460</xref>). Harpur adopts particular Darkinyung, Gamilaraay and
  HRLM words whose sound and meaning allows him to comprehend the
  landscape more fully. This is why I say his representation of
  Indigenous language is <italic>verbal</italic> and
  <italic>oral</italic>—he sees language as a collection of
  <italic>words</italic> that are <italic>spoken</italic> to denote
  particular things.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="linguistic-representation-and-the-conquest-of-space-nb-article">
  <title>4 Linguistic representation and the conquest of space</title>
  <p>Both Dunlop and Harpur claim poetic authority, and seek to write an
  Australian poetry which somehow reconciles the rights of white
  settlers and Indigenous Australians. In both cases, however, the white
  poet asserts the right to choose: to open the pantry of Indigenous
  poetry, and select the choicest morsels for their own compositions.
  Today this might be condemned as cultural appropriation
  (<xref alt="O’Leary 2004, 85" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">O’Leary
  2004, 85</xref>;
  <xref alt="Johnston 2021, 47" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
  2021, 47</xref>), but neither Dunlop nor Harpur seem to have been
  concerned that linguistic “borrowings” could be a kind of theft. It
  was simply obvious to Harpur and Dunlop that words don’t belong to
  anybody. Why not? In this section, I sketch the linguistic philosphy
  that justified their attitudes.</p>
  <p>In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, the empiricist philosophy of language
  predominated in the English-speaking world. Dunlop was well-versed in
  British empiricism, having read David Hume by the age of 12
  (<xref alt="Hansord 2021, 76" rid="ref-hansord_imperial_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hansord
  2021, 76</xref>). Harpur’s education is not well attested, but he was
  a close reader of Percy Shelley, whose debts to radical empiricism are
  well known.</p>
  <p>In the empiricist theory of language, language is made up of
  “signs,” and these “signs” are simply labels that we apply to objects
  we perceive
  (<xref alt="Bergheaud 1985, 159" rid="ref-bergheaud_empiricism_1985-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Bergheaud
  1985, 159</xref>). As Locke
  (<xref alt="1975, 405" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  405</xref>) argues, signs are arbitrary: words become signs for our
  ideas through “voluntary imposition.” Initially, we label “simple
  ideas,” such as <italic>red</italic>, <italic>wood</italic> or
  <italic>water</italic>. Later, we stitch together simple ideas to
  build up “complex ideas,” and label these complex ideas with signs
  such as <italic>government</italic> or <italic>religion</italic>
  (<xref alt="1975, sec. 3.2" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  sec. 3.2</xref>). Locke’s view is psychological and individualistic.
  My perceptual system delivers sensations into my mind, and I choose to
  label them with other sensations, namely sounds and visible
  characters, which then become signs. Locke was accordingly sceptical
  of abstract concepts. Ultimately a word is only meaningful if it can
  be reduced to simple, perceptible ideas such as <italic>hard</italic>
  or <italic>round</italic>. But when we use abstract words such as
  <italic>power</italic>, it is easy to forget the complex of particular
  sensations that the word refers to. Thus we often “have very good and
  approved Words in [our] Mouths, and Writings, with very uncertain,
  little or no signification”
  (<xref alt="1975, 438" rid="ref-locke_essay_1975-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1975,
  438</xref>).</p>
  <p>In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, the most famous proponent of Locke’s
  ideas was John Horne Tooke
  (<xref alt="Aarsleff 1967, chap. 2" rid="ref-aarsleff_study_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Aarsleff
  1967, chap. 2</xref>). Tooke
  (<xref alt="1805, vol. 1" rid="ref-tooke_epea_1805-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1805,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 18) begins with the proposition that “Words are the
  <italic>signs</italic> of <italic>things</italic>,” and then poses a
  difficult problem: there are many words, such as prepositions and
  articles, which do not refer to perceptible things. You cannot smell
  <italic>an</italic> or touch <italic>of</italic>. To save the
  empiricist theory of language, he attempts to prove that words such as
  <italic>an</italic> or <italic>of</italic> are “abbrevations” of nouns
  and verbs, offering some very inventive etymologies to illustrate his
  theory. He justifies the theory by observing that the human mind has
  an innate love of “<italic>dispatch</italic>”
  (<xref alt="1805, vol. 1" rid="ref-tooke_epea_1805-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1805,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 27). We wish to speak quickly, therefore we
  abbreviate, and generate all the abstract words of a fully
  grammaticizised language. Tooke’s ideas were later promulgated by the
  utilitarians, who in turn influenced the young Tennyson and Browning
  (<xref alt="Cooper 2006, 642–43" rid="ref-cooper_womens_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Cooper
  2006, 642–43</xref>). In his posthumous writings on language, Jeremy
  Bentham
  (<xref alt="1843" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1843</xref>)
  argues that every “sign” in language stands for some “entity,” and
  distinguishes “real” from “fictitious” entities. A “real” entity is
  “an object, the existence of which is made known to us by one or more
  of our five senses”; a “fictitious” entity is “an object, the
  existence of which is feigned by the imagination”
  (<xref alt="1843, 325" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1843,
  325</xref>). A word denoting a “fictitious” entity can only be
  meaningful if the fictitious entity can be broken down into real,
  perceptible entities: to every word with an “immaterial import there
  belongs, or at least did belong, a material one”
  (<xref alt="1843, 329" rid="ref-bentham_essay_1843-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1843,
  329</xref>). For Tooke, Bentham, and their empiricist forebears, human
  language is universal. Everywhere the operations of the mind are the
  same. Everywhere the mind encounters the same kind of material things.
  Since words are names for things, I can always understand the meaning
  of a word by learning what things it refers to, even when the word
  seems to denote an abstract concept.</p>
  <p>This analysis reveals that Dunlop’s universalism and Harpur’s
  particularism are two sides of the same coin. Harpur’s particularism
  would be impossible without the universality of the mind. Dunlop’s
  universality would be impossible without the particularity of the
  senses. Harpur asserts the universality of the human mind in mystical
  poems such as <italic>The Tower of the Dream</italic> (1851-53, h642a)
  and <italic>Cosmoplasticus</italic> (1857, h696c). In the major work
  of his maturity, <italic>The Witch of Hebron</italic> (1867, h689-gd),
  he suggests that each person originates alike in an “aboriginal
  inception, / […] A self-producing knot of living
  shoots[.]”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-nb-article">10</xref> Thus Harpur’s
  particularism has a universalist substrate. By contrast, Dunlop’s
  universalism expresses itself in particularism. We have already seen
  how she amplifies Wulatji’s text with sensory images, explicitly
  evoking the sounds, sights and feelings that Wulatji himself leaves
  implicit. In other poems, she describes particular places in loving
  detail, as in this stanza on her home at Mulla Villa:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>    Deep, silent water—water dark and still,
        Bowered in the desert, lonely lot is thine!
        For thee, no courtly Bard, essays his skill
    At thy cool font inspired—“sweet Mulla mine.”
    (<xref alt="Dunlop 2021, 198" rid="ref-dunlop_selection_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    2021, 198</xref>)</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>In this stanza, she evokes the sights and sounds of her home
  (“silent water—water dark”) in order to particularise it: her “Mulla,”
  the creek behind her home, is <italic>not</italic> the “Mulla” where
  the “courtly bard” Edmund Spenser lived in the sixteenth century.</p>
  <p>Harpur is traditionally labelled “Romantic” (e.g. by
  <xref alt="Kane 1996" rid="ref-kane_australian_1996-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Kane
  1996</xref>;
  <xref alt="Kelly and Fotheringham 1987" rid="ref-harpur_general_1987-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Kelly
  and Fotheringham 1987</xref>), while his female contemporaries such as
  Dunlop are labelled “sentimental.” Harpur and Dunlop’s shared
  empiricism, however, suggests that this distinction is illusory. Like
  earlier Romantics, such as Samuel Taylor Coleridge or Felicia Hemans,
  both Harpur and Dunlop seek the “One Mind” that is immanent in
  experience. Wu
  (<xref alt="2021, 69" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2021,
  69</xref>) is therefore quite correct when he writes: “Dunlop realised
  as clearly as any of the Romantic poets that art lives in the realm of
  the ideal” (see also
  <xref alt="Minter 2021, 109" rid="ref-minter_settlement_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Minter
  2021, 109</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hansord 2021, 79" rid="ref-hansord_imperial_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hansord
  2021, 79</xref>).</p>
  <p>What does Dunlop and Harpur’s empiricism have to do with the
  ownership of words? We can answer this question by comparing the
  then-dominant English theory of language with the then-dominant German
  theory. In Harpur and Dunlop’s time, German scholars had rejected the
  tradition of “philosophical grammar” represented by Locke, Tooke and
  Bentham, and were pursuing the new discipline of “historical
  philology”
  (<xref alt="Foucault 2002, xii" rid="ref-foucault_order_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Foucault
  2002, xii</xref>;
  <xref alt="Aarsleff 1967, 3–6" rid="ref-aarsleff_study_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Aarsleff
  1967, 3–6</xref>). In historical philology, the sign is no longer an
  arbitrary label for a sensation. Instead, words themselves are objects
  that have their own histories, can they cannot simply be detached from
  the languages of which they form a part. As Foucault
  (<xref alt="2002, 256" rid="ref-foucault_order_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  256</xref>) puts it, in historical philology, language has an
  “interior ‘mechanism’” that determines the distribution and
  interrelations of words. If this is the case, then linguistic
  borrowing becomes problematic. One of the early proponents of
  historical philology, Johann Gottfried Herder
  (<xref alt="1993, 38–39" rid="ref-herder_against_1993-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1993,
  38–39</xref>) illustrates the problem:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>You must first enter the spirit of a nation in order to empathize
    completely with even one of its thoughts or deeds. You must discover
    a characterizing word through which you can understand everything in
    depth. Otherwise, you simply read a word.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>A word is not a name applied by an individual to a sensation; it is
  the expression of the “spirit of a nation.” If you do not know this
  “spirit,” you do not “understand” the word, you simply “read” it.
  Herder’s argument invalidates Dunlop’s procedure of swapping one word
  for another in her translation: “bato” (<italic>paTu</italic>) cannot
  translate “kokein” (<italic>kukuyn</italic>): these are different
  words, even if they refer to the same object of perception. Herder’s
  argument also invalidates Harpur’s procedure of selecting words for
  their “euphoniousness:” Harpur has merely “read” the word for its
  sounds, rather than grasping its spirit.</p>
  <p>One implication of historical philology is that human nature
  changes. Human nature is “a pliant clay, which assumes different
  shapes under different circumstances, needs, and burdens”
  (<xref alt="Herder 1993, 43" rid="ref-herder_against_1993-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Herder
  1993, 43</xref>). This view of human nature undermines the
  metaphysical presuppositions of Harpur and Dunlop’s poetry. There is
  no one mind that expresses itself in song, as Dunlop believed. We do
  not live in a shared world of particulars that guarantee the meaning
  of words, as Harpur believed. Herder and the historicists could not
  endorse Dunlop and Harpur’s programme.</p>
  <p>This analysis indicates precisely why it is anachronistic to accuse
  Harpur and Dunlop of “cultural appropriation.” In their view, words
  were labels for perceptions, and it was open to any person at any time
  to invent or adopt a new
  label.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-nb-article">11</xref> Since words do not
  belong to a “culture,” they cannot be stolen from one. When Dunlop and
  Harpur conquered space, they did not do so by stealing its names, but
  by enriching the English language so its speakers could name
  Australia. To enrich the English language, they produced
  representations of Indigenous language: a transcription, a
  translation, a glossary, and philological footnotes. This does not
  absolve them of imperial ambition. When they named Australia, they
  helped to take the things they named, even if they did not mean to
  take the names themselves.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusion-agony-nb-article">
  <title>5 Conclusion: Agony</title>
  <p>Dunlop and Harpur make themselves at home in Australia only in an
  agony of conscience. Other colonial poets were not so agonised. Emily
  Manning
  (<xref alt="1877, 43" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1877,
  43</xref>), for example, ends her otherwise beautiful poem “From the
  Clyde to Braidwood” on this dismissive note:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>            —no legend old
    Adds softening beauty to the Buddawong Peak,
    Or near home-ranges with too barbarous names.</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Manning can read no “legend” in the landscape, and dismisses the
  local names of the Braidwood district as “barbarous”—even though she
  uses three Indigenous Australian words in the poem, namely
  “Currawong,” “Kurrajong” and (in these very lines) “Buddawong.” She
  describes the road from Clyde to Braidwood in wonderful detail, but
  the only human activity she can see there is the activity of the white
  man who has “cleft the rock” to build the road
  (<xref alt="Manning 1877, 42" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Manning
  1877, 42</xref>). The poem is a mature expression of a Australian
  tradition inaugrated by Barron Field, who established in both law and
  poetry the doctrine of <italic>terra nullius</italic>
  (<xref alt="Ford and Clemens 2023" rid="ref-ford_barron_2023-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  and Clemens 2023</xref>). To Manning’s eyes, the land is empty, its
  past is untold, and if it has names, they are “barbarous.” Braidwood
  itself is therefore “new, new, too new / To foster Poesy”
  (<xref alt="Manning 1877, 43" rid="ref-manning_balance_1877-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Manning
  1877, 43</xref>).</p>
  <p>Neither Harpur nor Dunlop were members of this tradition. Both
  found poetry in the Australian landscape, and acknowledged that
  Indigenous Australians had found it first. They attempted to convey
  this poetry to colonial readers by setting forth the riches of
  Indigenous speech and writing. Dunlop presented Wulatji as a bard in
  the tradition of world poetry, and treated Awabakal (HRLM) as a
  classical language of civilisation. Harpur presented his Darkinyung,
  Gamilaraay and Wonnarua informants as skilled workers of the land, who
  had seen and named myriad beauties of the world. Though Dunlop and
  Harpur adopted different means to represent Indigenous languages,
  their underlying philosophy was similar, as was their agony, which was
  to “[reinscribe] the logic of colonisation” in the face of its
  injustice
  (<xref alt="Minter 2021, 113" rid="ref-minter_settlement_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Minter
  2021, 113</xref>). They wrote vexed and contradictory poetry, whose
  vexation has lost none of its pertinence in the third century of
  Australia’s colonisation.</p>
  <p>Wulatji, meanwhile, can speak for himself.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements-nb-article">
  <title>6 Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>I am grateful to Jim Wafer and Grace Karskens for sharing their
  unpublished notes on Harpur’s <italic>Kangaroo Hunt</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</body>



<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-wulatji_native_1848-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Wulatji</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Native Poetry</article-title>
      <source>The Sydney Morning Herald</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1848-10">1848</year><month>10</month>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article12904464</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dixon_australian_2006-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Bruce</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ramson</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Mandy</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Australian Aboriginal Words in English: Their Origin and Meaning</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      <edition>Second Edition</edition>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-falk_endless_2019-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Endless Forms of Things: Harpur’s Radicalism Revisited</article-title>
      <source>Journal of the Association for the Study of Australian Literature</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-02">2019</year><month>02</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-09-24">2019</year><month>09</month><day>24</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>18</issue>
      <issn>1833-6027</issn>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/index.php/JASAL/article/view/13026</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ackland_charles_1983-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ackland</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur’s &quot;the bush fire&quot; and &quot;a storm in the mountains&quot;: Sublimity, cognition and faith</article-title>
      <source>Southerly</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1983-12">1983</year><month>12</month>
      <volume>43</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <issn>0038-3732</issn>
      <fpage>459</fpage>
      <lpage>474</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-aarsleff_study_1967-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Aarsleff</surname><given-names>Hans</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Study of Language in England, 1780-1860</source>
      <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1967">1967</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dixon_charles_1980-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur and John Gould</article-title>
      <source>Southerly</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1980-09">1980</year><month>09</month>
      <volume>40</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <issn>0038-3732</issn>
      <fpage>315</fpage>
      <lpage>329</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-mead_charles_1990-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur’s Disfiguring Origins: Allegory in Colonial Poetry</article-title>
      <source>Australian Literary Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1990">1990</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>279</fpage>
      <lpage>296</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-kane_australian_1996-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Australian Poetry: Romanticism and Negativity</source>
      <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-locke_essay_1975-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Nidditch</surname><given-names>Peter H.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-van_toorn_terrors_1992-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Van Toorn</surname><given-names>Penny</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Terrors of Terra Nullius: Gothicising and De‐Gothicising aboriginality</article-title>
      <source>World Literature Written in English</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1992">1992</year>
      <volume>32</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17449859208589194</pub-id>
      <fpage>87</fpage>
      <lpage>97</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-troy_sydney_1993-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>Jakelin</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Sydney Language</source>
      <publisher-name>Jakelin Troy</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-oleary_giving_2004-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Giving the indigenous a voice — further thoughts on the poetry of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Australian Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2004-01">2004</year><month>01</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2019-07-16">2019</year><month>07</month><day>16</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>28</volume>
      <issue>82</issue>
      <issn>1444-3058</issn>
      <uri>https://doi.org/10.1080/14443050409387958</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14443050409387958</pub-id>
      <fpage>85</fpage>
      <lpage>93</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-lissarrague_salvage_2006-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Lissarrague</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>A salvage grammar and wordlist of the language from the Hunter River and Lake Macquarie</source>
      <publisher-name>Muurrbay Aboriginal Language; Culture Cooperative</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Nambucca Heads, NSW</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      <isbn>978-0-9775351-0-1</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-foucault_order_2002-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Order of Things: An Archaeology of the Human Sciences</source>
      <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_general_1987-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Veronica</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Fotheringham</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>General Editors’ Preface</article-title>
      <source>Stalwart the Bushranger, with The Tragedy of Donohoe</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Currency Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1987">1987</year>
      <fpage>vi</fpage>
      <lpage>x</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-eggert_charles_2016-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Eggert</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Charles Harpur: The Editorial Nightmare</article-title>
      <source>JASAL</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/JASAL/article/view/11011</uri>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>14</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-webby_representations_2013-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Representations of ’The Bush’ in the Poetry of Charles Harpur</article-title>
      <source>JASAL</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <uri>https://openjournals.library.sydney.edu.au/JASAL/article/view/10266</uri>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>8</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_charles_2019-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harpur</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Charles Harpur Critical Archive</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Eggert</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-683-1</isbn>
      <uri>http://charles-harpur.org/</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-carter_road_2010-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The road to Botany Bay: An exploration of landscape and history</source>
      <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <isbn>978-0-8166-6997-4</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wafer</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Ghost-writing for Wulatji: Incubation and re-dreaming as song revitalisation practices</article-title>
      <source>Recirculating Songs: Revitalising the singing practices of Indigenous Australia</source>
      <publisher-name>Hunter Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Newcastle</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-01-07">2020</year><month>01</month><day>07</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>https://openresearch-repository.anu.edu.au/bitstream/1885/132161/18/9_wafer.pdf</uri>
      <fpage>193</fpage>
      <lpage>256</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
        <string-name>Wulatji</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Pialla Wollombi</article-title>
      <source>The Southern Euphrosyne and Australian Miscellany: Containing oriental moral takes, original anecdote, poetry and music</source>
      <publisher-name>Whittaker &amp; Co.</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London; Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1848">1848</year>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-166023361</uri>
      <fpage>94</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-tuan_space_1977-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>Yi-Fu</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Space and Place: The Perspective of Experience</source>
      <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1977">1977</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-gelder_colonial_2020-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gelder</surname><given-names>Ken</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>Rachael</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The Colonial Kangaroo Hunt</source>
      <publisher-name>Melbourne University Publishing</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-06">2024</year><month>05</month><day>06</day></date-in-citation>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-0-522-87586-7</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_selection_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A Selection of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop’s Poems</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>175</fpage>
      <lpage>204</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-johnston_proud_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>“Proud of Contributing Its Quota to the Original Literature of the Colony” : An Introduction to Eliza Hamilton Dunlop and Her Writing</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>8</fpage>
      <lpage>30</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wafer_unmapping_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wafer</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Unmapping the Mulla : Dunlop and the Villa on Wollombi Brook</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>154</fpage>
      <lpage>173</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-minter_settlement_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Minter</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Settlement Defiled : Ventriloquy, Pollution and Nature in Eliza Hamilton Dunlops’ ’The Aboriginal Mother’</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>103</fpage>
      <lpage>115</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-rudy_beyond_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>Jason R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Beyond Universalisms : Individuation, Race and Sentiment in Colonial New South Wales</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>91</fpage>
      <lpage>101</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-hansord_imperial_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Hansord</surname><given-names>Katrina</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Imperial Feminism and “My Father’s Library” : Intellectual, Literary and Political Thought in Eliza Hamilton Dunlop’s Poetry</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>74</fpage>
      <lpage>90</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-wu_morning_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Duncan</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>“Morning on Rostrevor Mountains” and the Making of Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>56</fpage>
      <lpage>73</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-johnston_poetry_2021-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Poetry of the Archive : Locating Eliza Hamilton Dunlop</article-title>
      <source>Eliza Hamilton Dunlop : Writing from the Colonial Frontier</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Sydney University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <edition>ebook</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-74332-748-7</isbn>
      <fpage>30</fpage>
      <lpage>54</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-harpur_australian_1843-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Harpur</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Australian Scenery (From the &quot;Kangaroo Hunt,&quot; an unpublished poem)</article-title>
      <source>Weekly Register of Politics, Facts and General Literature</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1843-11">1843</year><month>11</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-08">2024</year><month>05</month><day>08</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article228135900</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-lissarrague_gamilaraay_2003-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <source>Gamilaraay, Yuwaalaraay &amp; Yuwaalayaay dictionary</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Lissarrague</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Giacon</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>IAD Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Alice Springs, N.T</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <isbn>978-1-86465-051-8</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ellis_dhurga_2020-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <source>The Dhurga dictionary and learner’s grammar: A south-east coast, NSW Aboriginal language</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Boyenga</surname><given-names>Kerry</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>Waine</given-names></name>
        <string-name>Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Aboriginal Studies Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Canberra, ACT</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <edition>1st</edition>
      <isbn>978-1-925302-60-8</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-jones_darkinyung_2008-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Darkinyung grammar and dictionary: Revitalising a language from historical sources</source>
      <publisher-name>Muurrbay Aboriginal Language; Culture Co-operative</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Nambucca Heads, N.S.W</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
      <isbn>978-0-9775351-9-4</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-grant_new_2010-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Stan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>Stan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rudder</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>A new Wiradjuri dictionary</source>
      <publisher-name>Restoration House</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>O’Connor, A.C.T</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <isbn>978-0-86942-150-5</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_poesy_1872-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Poesy</article-title>
      <source>Australian Town and Country Journal</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, NSW</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1872-10">1872</year><month>10</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2020-11-03">2020</year><month>11</month><day>03</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article70497610</uri>
      <fpage>20</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-cooper_womens_2006-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Andrew R.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Women’s Poetry, the 1830s, and Monumental Problems in the History of Language Theory.</article-title>
      <source>Women’s Studies</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006-10">2006</year><month>10</month>
      <volume>35</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <issn>0049-7878</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00497870600904144</pub-id>
      <fpage>621</fpage>
      <lpage>655</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-bergheaud_empiricism_1985-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bergheaud</surname><given-names>Patrice</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Empiricism and linguistics in eighteenth-century Great Britain</article-title>
      <source>Topoi</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1985-09">1985</year><month>09</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-15">2024</year><month>05</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <issn>0167-7411, 1572-8749</issn>
      <uri>http://link.springer.com/10.1007/BF00135843</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00135843</pub-id>
      <fpage>155</fpage>
      <lpage>163</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-tooke_epea_1805-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tooke</surname><given-names>John Horne</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Epea pteroenta. Or, the diversions of Purley</source>
      <publisher-name>J. Johnson</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1805">1805</year>
      <edition>Second Edition</edition>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_vase_nodate-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="manuscript">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The Vase, comprising songs for music and poems</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>State Library of New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <uri>https://collection.sl.nsw.gov.au/record/Yold2BN9</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dunlop_mind_1872-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>Eliza Hamilton</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Mind</article-title>
      <source>Evening News</source>
      <publisher-loc>Sydney, New South Wales</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1872-06">1872</year><month>06</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-15">2024</year><month>05</month><day>15</day></date-in-citation>
      <uri>http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article114733889</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-geoscience_australia_geodata_2003-nb-article">
    <element-citation>
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Geoscience Australia</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>GEODATA TOPO 2.5M</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
      <uri>https://pid.geoscience.gov.au/dataset/ga/60804</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-bentham_essay_1843-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Bentham</surname><given-names>Jeremy</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Essay on Language</article-title>
      <source>The works of Jeremy Bentham</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Bowring</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>W. Tait</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1843">1843</year>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <edition>1st</edition>
      <fpage>294</fpage>
      <lpage>357</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-herder_against_1993-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Herder</surname><given-names>Johann Gottfried von</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Against pure reason: Writings on religion, language, and history</source>
      <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1993">1993</year>
      <isbn>978-0-8006-3212-0</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-manning_balance_1877-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>The balance of pain : And other poems</source>
      <publisher-name>London: G. Bell</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="1877">1877</year>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-05-20">2024</year><month>05</month><day>20</day></date-in-citation>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-ford_barron_2023-nb-article">
    <element-citation publication-type="book">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>Thomas H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <source>Barron field in New South Wales: The poetics of Terra Nullius</source>
      <publisher-name>Melbourne University Press</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Carlton, Victoria</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year>
      <isbn>978-0-522-87878-3</isbn>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1-nb-article">
    <label>1</label><p>She later adapted the poem for Isaac Nathan’s
    song collection, <italic>The Southern Euphrosyne</italic>
    (<xref alt="Dunlop and Wulatji 1848" rid="ref-dunlop_pialla_1848-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dunlop
    and Wulatji 1848</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn2-nb-article">
    <label>2</label><p>Paul Eggert’s variorum edition of Harpur’s poetry
    provides an ‘h-number’ for each version of each poem. I refer to
    Harpur’s poems by h-number throughout. Each of <italic>Kangaroo
    Hunt</italic>’s six parts has its own h-number.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn3-nb-article">
    <label>3</label><p>In another poem of the same year, she extols the
    universality of “IMPERIAL MIND!”, which compels “Obedience”
    throughout its “boundless realm”
    (<xref alt="1872a" rid="ref-dunlop_mind_1872-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1872a</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn4-nb-article">
    <label>4</label><p>Her brothers were not so friendly. They refused
    to acknowledge their Indian half-sisters, and denied them their
    inheritance
    (<xref alt="Johnston 2021, 39" rid="ref-johnston_poetry_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Johnston
    2021, 39</xref>;
    <xref alt="Wu 2021, 63" rid="ref-wu_morning_2021-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wu
    2021, 63</xref>)</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn5-nb-article">
    <label>5</label><p>According to Threlkeld, Wulatji was a popular
    guest, whose humourous ‘gibes’ and ‘song and dance’ routines were
    highly appreciated by Indigenous people throughout the region
    (quoted in
    <xref alt="Wafer 2017, 200" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wafer
    2017, 200</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn6-nb-article">
    <label>6</label><p>On the coincidence between Wulatji’s name and
    Wallatu’s, see O’Leary
    (<xref alt="2004, 91" rid="ref-oleary_giving_2004-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2004,
    91</xref>) and Wafer
    (<xref alt="2017, 199" rid="ref-wafer_ghost-writing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017,
    199</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn7-nb-article">
    <label>7</label><p>I am indebted to Jim Wafer for sharing his notes
    on Harpur’s Indigenous vocabulary, which helped especially with the
    difficult <italic>teleltella</italic>.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn8-nb-article">
    <label>8</label><p>Harpur’s name never caught on, although Henry
    Kendall borrowed it for his own kangaroo hunt poem. Kendall was
    apparently unaware the “Jehu” is a colloquial term for a coachman,
    and changed the spelling to “echu,” emphasising its onomatopoeia
    (<xref alt="Gelder and Weaver 2020, 73" rid="ref-gelder_colonial_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Gelder
    and Weaver 2020, 73</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn9-nb-article">
    <label>9</label><p>The word is Harpur’s. See for instance h185b.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn10-nb-article">
    <label>10</label><p>This image does suggest a “developmental”
    viewpoint that is superficially similar to Herder’s historicism; but
    Harpur’s view of development was more teleological that Herder’s
    (<xref alt="Falk 2019, 6–10" rid="ref-falk_endless_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Falk
    2019, 6–10</xref>).</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn11-nb-article">
    <label>11</label><p>How Wulatji and other Indigenous informants
    viewed these linguistic “borrowings” I do not know.</p>
  </fn>
</fn-group>
</back>


</sub-article>

</article>